<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The table of Cebes the philosopher. How one may take profite of his enemies, translated out of Plutarche. A treatise perswadyng a man paciently to suffer the death of his freend</title>
            <title>Pinax. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1545</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 106 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 79 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18296</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4891</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109138</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844788</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844788</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9631</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18296)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9631)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 30:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The table of Cebes the philosopher. How one may take profite of his enemies, translated out of Plutarche. A treatise perswadyng a man paciently to suffer the death of his freend</title>
                  <title>Pinax. English.</title>
                  <author>Plutarch. De capienda ex inimicis utilitate. aut</author>
                  <author>Erasmus, Desiderius, d. 1536. De morte declamatio. aut</author>
                  <author>Poyntz, Francis, Sir, d. 1528.</author>
                  <author>Elyot, Thomas, Sir, 1490?-1546, attributed name.</author>
                  <author>Cebes, of Thebes, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[160] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In fletestreete by Thomas Berthelet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1545?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, by Sir Francis Poyntz, of "Pinax", which is not in fact by Cebes.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>"How one maie take profite of his enemies" (a translation, possibly by Sir Thomas Elyot, of Plutarch's "De capienda ex inimicis utilitate", reprinted from STC 20052), and "A comfortable exhortacion against the chances of death" (a translation, also possibly by Sir Thomas Elyot, of: Erasmus' "De morte declamatio", reprinted from STC 10476.3) with caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-K.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9631:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9631:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE TABLE OF CEBES THE PHILO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SOPHER.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶How one may take pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of his ennemies, tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated out of Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarche.</p>
            <p>¶A treatiſe perſwadyng a man paciently to ſuffer the death of his freend.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:9631:2"/>
            <head>The Printer to the reader.</head>
            <p>THis table of Cebes, ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing how mortall crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, blinded by Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, wander in this worlde, and can not atteyne to very Felicitee, for that they be myſled by falſe opinions; and wrong weenynges: was tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated out of latine into engliſh by ſir Frances Poyngz, at the requeſt of his brother ſir Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Poyngz, which tranſlacion is woorthy of high commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. And if any faute be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, I knowe well, it is miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng, for my copie was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what combrouſe, what for the enterlinyng and yll writyng.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:9631:2"/>
            <head>The table of Cebes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T chanced vs to walke in the Temple of Saturne, where among many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gyftes and oblacions, that we ſawe, a Table was hanged vp, for an offryng. In the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che was a picture very ſtrange, conteinyng in it certaine fables and ſtories. The which we coud neyther coniecte whereof they were, nor of what tyme they were. For that that was pein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, nother ſemed to vs to be a citie, nor a fortreſſe, but there was in it one great circle or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:9631:3"/>
conteinyng within it two other circles, the one more, and the other leſſe. There was alſo a gate in the fyrſt circle, and in the gate there ſeemed to vs a great compaigny to ſtand: And within the cloſure there appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a multitude of women. In the entryng of the firſt poarche and circuite there ſtode an olde man, whiche ſeemed as though he commaunded ſomewhat to the companie, that entred in.</p>
            <p>A fatherly man ſtandyng by vs, and ſeyng vs muſe &amp; doubt of this picture long time among our ſelues, ſaied vnto vs: You ſtraungers, bee not aſſhamed, though ye doubt what this py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture is. For there be many, that dwell in this citie, that wot full
<pb facs="tcp:9631:3"/>
litel what the inuencion of this Table betokeneth. For, for to ſaie trouth, none of this Citee offered it, but a certaine ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in tyme paſte came hither, a wyſe man and a noble philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, folowyng both in woorde and deede the lyfe of Pythago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras and Parmenides: who dyd builde this temple in the honor of Saturne, and alſo did offer vp to the ſame this picture. Did you euer, ſaied I, knowe that ſame man by ſight? Yea, ſaied he, and had hym long tyme in great reuerence. For all be it he was but younge, yet did he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, and diſpute, many thyngꝭ cunnyngly. And I haue hearde him talkyng often of the inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of this picture. For goddis
<pb facs="tcp:9631:4"/>
ſake than, quoth I, excepte ye haue ſome other great buſines, declare it vnto vs. For we great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly couet to know, what this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſignifieth. With good wyll freendes, quoth he, but ye muſte vnderſtand, that the declaraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it is perillous. Howe ſo quoth I? For, quod he, if ye at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentifly herken and vnderſtand that that is ſaid, ye ſhal be both wyſe and happie. If ye do not, ye ſhall be made bothe vnwyſe, vnhappie, heauy and rude, and leade all your life after miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly. For this tale is like the rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell of Spinx, that ſhe purpoſed to folke: the whiche if any body vnderſtode, he was ſafe, if he vnderſtode it not, he was ſlaine of Spinx. The ſame maner is
<pb facs="tcp:9631:4"/>
in this tale. For folie is to me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a Spinx. And ſhe alſo purpoſeth to folke, what is good, what is yll, what is not good, what is not yll in this lyfe. Theſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges except a man vnderſtand, he is ſlayne of folie: But not vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly, as he that is deuoured of Spinx, but a littell and a littell in al the whole life is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumed, lyke as they that be delyuered continually to be tourmented. But if a man vnderſtand theſe thynges contrariewyſe, folie is loſt, the man is ſaued and made bliſfull and happy al his life af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Wherfore attend ye dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and myſhere me not. O good lord, into what a greedie deſire haſt thou brought vs, if thoſe thynges be as thou ſaieſt? And
<pb facs="tcp:9631:5"/>
I (quoth he) enſure you they be ſo. Well thou ſhalt not preuent vs in tellyng: For we will her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken diligently, ſeyng the penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is ſuche.</p>
            <p>He toke then a rod, and poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to the picture. See you not, quoth he, this circuite. We ſee it. This ye muſt firſt know, that this place is called life: And the great companie, that ſtandeth before the doore, be thoſe that ſhall enter into lyfe. The olde man, that ſtandeth aboue, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng in his one hande a paper, and with the other, as it were ſhewyng ſomewhat, is called Genius, He commaundeth the entrers, what they muſte dooe, if they wyll be kepte ſafe in the lyfe. What waie doeth he bidde
<pb facs="tcp:9631:5"/>
them go, and how, ꝙ I? Seeſt thou not (quoth he) hard by the gate, a certaine ſeate, ſet in the place, where the great compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny entreth: in the whiche there ſitteth a woman goodly of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, with a fayre luryng coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinance, and hauyng in hir ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d a cuppe? I ſee hir, but what is ſhe, quoth I? She is called Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite, quoth he, myſleader of all folke. Than what dooeth ſhe? She compelleth them, that come into the lyfe to drinke as muche of hir cuppe as ſhe can. What drinke? It is, quoth he, errour and ignoraunce. What than? Whan they haue droncke that drinke they enter into lyfe. whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than do all folke drinke er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror or no? All drinke (quoth he)
<pb facs="tcp:9631:6"/>
but ſome more, ſome leſſe. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, ſeeſt thou not within the gate a great ſort of women, hauyng diuers horiſhe tatches? I ſee them. Thoſe be called opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, deſires, and luſtes. As ſoone as the companie entreth, thoſe leape foorth and embrace euerie one of theim, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward conuey them away. whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do thei bryng them? Some bryng theim, quoth he, to ſaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde, and ſome to deſtruction by Diſceit. O marueilous god, what a ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge drink telleſt thou of. But al theſe forſaid women, quoth he, do promiſe, as though they would leade the entrers to the beſt thingꝭ, and alſo to a life happie, profitable, and commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious: the entrers then through
<pb facs="tcp:9631:6"/>
the Ignoraunce and Erroure, that thei dronke by Deceite, can not fynde, whiche is the trewe way in the life, but wander vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduiſedly: as thou ſeeſt theim that came in firſt, the whiche ſeme to wander thither, as thoſe women poinct them. I ſee that, quod I, but that woman, what is ſhe, the whiche ſeemeth as it were one blind and madde: and ſtandeth vpon a rounde ſtone? She is called, quod he, Fortune ſhe is not only blynde, but alſo madde and deaffe. What doeth ſhe? She walketh euery where, quoth he, and from ſome ſhe ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth rycheſſe: to ſome other ſhe geueth: and from them by and by ſhe taketh agayne that, that ſhe gaue them before, and dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth
<pb facs="tcp:9631:7"/>
it to ſome other, bothe without cauſe, without aduiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; inconſtantly. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that token declareth well hir nature. what token is that, quoth I, that ſhe ſtandeth vpon a round ſtone? what betokeneth that? Marie that hir geftes be bothe vncertaine and vnſtable. Wherfore they that truſte vnto hir, ſuffer ſharpe and greuouſe troubles. But what meaneth the great companie that ſtande about hir, and what be thei cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led? Certainly thei be called folk without iudgement or conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racion. For euery one of theim dooeth aſke thoſe thynges, that be bothe tranſitorie and vaniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyng. Wherfore than doe they not looke all a lyke, but ſome of
<pb facs="tcp:9631:7"/>
them do ſeme to reioice, and ſom of them be ſorowfull, heuy, and caſtyng abroade their handes? Thoſe which ſeme (quoth he) to reioyce and laughe, be of them, the whiche haue receiued ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of Fortune, and thoſe cal hir good Fortune: But thoſe, whiche ſeme to weepe and caſt out their handes, bee of theim, from whom ſhe hath take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that the whiche ſhe gaue them before: And thoſe call hir yll Fortune. What thynges bee thoſe than, the whiche ſhe geueth them, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng that the receiuours reioyce ſo muche in receiuyng of theim, and the loaſers dooe ſo muche droupe and mourne for the loſſe of them? Thoſe thynges (quoth he) the whiche many folkes call
<pb facs="tcp:9631:8"/>
goodes. Ye but whiche be they? Richeſſe, quoth he, and glorie, and nobilitee, and children, and lordſhyp, and kyngdomes, and other ſuche lyke. Why be not thoſe thynges good in deede? As of that (quoth he) we ſhall diſpute an other tyme: but now let vs go foorth with this tale. Be it ſo.</p>
            <p>¶Se ye not then, after ye haue paſſed this gate, another higher compace, and women ſtandyng without the ſame circuite ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poincted lyke harlottes? Ye ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raie well. The one of thoſe is called Incontinence, an other Riot, an other Couetiſe, an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Flattery. Why dooe they than ſtande here? They await duely vpon theim, the whiche
<pb facs="tcp:9631:8"/>
haue receiued any thing of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. What than? Than they ſkippe forth and imbrace them, and flatter, and praie theim to abide with theim, ſeeyng, that thei ſo doyng ſhall haue a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt life without any labour, griefe or trouble. Than if any of theim be perſwaded by thoſe women to enter into pleaſure, ſo longe as that conuerſacion tyckleth and delyteth hym, ſo longe he ſhall thincke it ſweete, but afterward it is not ſo. For as ſoone as he calleth him ſelfe home, he ſhal well perceiue, that he hath not eaten pleaſure, but that he hath been by pleaſure bothe eaten and wronged. For when he hath conſumed al that Fortune gaue hym, he is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled
<pb facs="tcp:9631:9"/>
to be thoſe wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſlaue, and to ſuffer al thynges, and to be filthy, and for their ſakes to leaue none vngracioꝰ dede vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doen: As to take mens goodes from theim, to committe ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, to forſweare and periure them ſelfe, to betraie, to robbe and roue, and to dooe all other ſuche lyke myſcheuous deedes: But whan all thynges doe fayle theim, than are they deliuered to peyne and tourment. What peyne and tourment is that?</p>
            <p>Seeſt thou not behynde yonder women (quoth he) as it were a littell mouthe of a caue, and a certain ſtraict and darke place: and alſo there ſemeth to ve wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men foule and ſluttiſh, and their clothes all baudie, ragged, and
<pb facs="tcp:9631:9"/>
beggerly? I ſee it well. Of theſe (ꝙ he) ſhe that hath the whippe in hir hande, is called Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Shee that hath hir head betwene hir knees, is Heauines: ſhe that plucketh hir own heare, is Sorowe. But what miſſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, leane, and naked felowe is he, that ſtandeth by theim: and alſo an other fowle and leane woman lyke vnto hym? The man is called (quoth he) Wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng, and ſhe his ſiſter is called Sluggiſhneſſe, or lacke of cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage. And ſo to thoſe perſons he is delyuered, and with theim he liueth in continuall turment. Than agayne from hence he is throwen into an other houſe of euill happe: and there he paſſeth foorth the reſt of his lyfe in all
<pb facs="tcp:9631:10"/>
miſery and wretchednes, except Repentance come to hym from Fortune. Why, what ſhall ſhe dooe? Marie if Repentaunce come to hym, ſhe deliuereth him from all euyles: and imprinteth in hym, an other opinion and deſyre, that ſhould leade him to true lernyng, and alſo to that, the whiche is called the vntrue learnyng. Than what is doen more? If he receyue (quoth he) the opinion, the whiche guideth him to true lernyng, by that he is purged: and made ſafe and bleſſed, and ſhall be happie all his life after, except he be again deceyued by falſe opinion. O good lord, what an other great peryll is this? But what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of thing, quod I, is the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true
<pb facs="tcp:9631:10"/>
learnyng? Seeſt thou not yonder other Compaſſe? Very well, quoth I. Alſo without the circuite aboute the entre, there ſtandeth a woman, the whiche ſeemeth to be veraie nette, and pure, and to be well manered. I ſee hir veraie well. Hir (quoth he) many fooliſhe folke call ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, but ſhee is none other in deede, than vntrue learnyng. And whan thei, that are wholly made ſafe, wyll aduance them ſelfe to true lernyng, they come hyther firſt. Is there than none other waie but this, to come to true learnyng? Yes, quoth he. But thoſe folkes within the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuite that go downward, what be they? Thoſe be, quoth he, the louers of vntrue learnyng, men
<pb facs="tcp:9631:11"/>
deceiued, and wenyng that thei be very familiare with true ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng. What bee they called? Some poetes, quoth he, ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratours, ſome Logiciens, ſome Muſiciens, ſome Arithmetrici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens, ſome Geometriciens, ſome Aſtronomers, ſome of Epicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res ſecte, ſome of the Peripate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike ſecte, ſome of the ſecte Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike, and all other ſuche lyke. The women, the whiche ſeeme to renne aboute, lyke to thoſe we ſawe firſt, among whom thou dydſt ſaie, there was In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continence, and other with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, what be they? The ſelfe ſame, quoth he. Why come they in hyther than? yea by Iupiter e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen hither: but that is ſeldome, and not as they doe in the firſt
<pb facs="tcp:9631:11"/>
compaſſe. And what, bee not thoſe opinions likewyſe? yes, quod he. Moreouer there remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in theſe folke the draughte that they dranke of Deceit both Ignoraunce, and with hir alſo fooliſhneſſe: And they ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be deliuered of opinion, nor of other malyce, till ſuche tyme as they haue forgotten the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true learnyng, and bee entered into the true waie, and drincke there a pourgeyng vertue, and caſte awaie all the euylles they had before, both opinions, Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, and all other vngraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe. Than vnder this faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thei ſhall be made whole. But theſe, the whiche remaine ſtyll with falſe lernyng, ſhal neuer be quitte of their naughtineſſe: nor
<pb facs="tcp:9631:12"/>
thei ſhall neuer be without ſome euill, for theſe ſtudies ſake. But which is this way, that leadeth a man to true learnyng? Seeſt thou, quoth he, yonder aboue, a place, in the whiche no bodie dwelleth, but it ſemeth to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerte? I ſee it. Moreouer there is a littell gate, and a waie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the gate, the whiche is not very muche haunted, very fewe folke vſe it, for becauſe it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth harde to clymme to it: and it is bothe rough and ſtonie? I ſee it very well, quoth I. There appereth alſo a littell high hill, and the aſcendyng vp is veraie ſtraict, and hath deepe pitchlin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges here and there, where one may lightly fall down hedlyng. I ſee it. This is the way, quoth
<pb facs="tcp:9631:12"/>
he, that leadeth vnto true lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng: and truely to loke to, it ſeemeth an vneaſy waie. Seeſt thou not alſo aboue about the hyll top a great high ſtone, very ſtiepe vp on euery ſide? I ſee it, quoth I. Seeſt thou alſo two goodly women ſtandyng vpon the ſtone with good proporcion of body, and how thei put forth their handes redy and gladly? I ſee them, but howe, quoth I, be thei called? The one, quod he is called Continence, the other Sufferaunce, they bee ſyſters. Why put thei out their handes ſo gladly? They doe, quoth he, exhorte the commers towarde that place to truſte, and not to feare, tellyng theim they muſte take a littell pacience and ſuffre
<pb facs="tcp:9631:13"/>
a littell whyle more, and than they ſhall come into the good waie. Tell me this, whan they come to the ſtone, how geat thei vp thereon, for I ſee no waie, that bringeth theim vp? Theſe women come downe from the ſtiepe clyffes, and drawe theim vp: and there they bidde theim reſt: and within a whyle after they geue theim ſtrength, cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and boldeneſſe: and they promiſe to ſtabliſh them in true learnyng: and they ſhewe them the waie, howe fayre, playne, and paſſable it is, and pure and cleane from all lettes or ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes, as thou ſeeſt. They ſhewe theim in deede. Seeſt thou not alſo, quoth he, before this ſame woodde a certayne place, the
<pb facs="tcp:9631:13"/>
whiche ſeemeth to be very faire, ſomewhat lyke a meddow, and ſhinyng with muche lyght and brightneſſe? Very well Dooeſt thou alſo take heede in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the meddow of an other compaſſe, and an other gate? It is ſo, but what is this place called? The habitacion of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed folke (quoth he.) For here dwell all vertues and felicitee. It muſt needes than be a fayre place, quoth I. Than thou ſeeſt at the gate a certayne woman, the whiche is veraie fayre, and of a conſtant face and behaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, in hir middel and luſly age, and hauyng hir apparell and garmentes ſymple: She ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not vpon a rounde ſtoane, but on a ſquare, ſurely ſet and
<pb facs="tcp:9631:14"/>
fixed: and with hir there be two other, thei ſeme to be hir dough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters? It appereth ſo. Of theſe, the myddelmoſte is Learnyng, the other Trouth, the other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion. But why ſtandeth this woman vpon a ſquare ſtoane? It is a token, quoth he, that the way, that leadeth folke to hir, is to theim bothe fyrme and ſure: and the gyft of thoſe thynges, that ſhe geueth, is to the receiuours ſure and ſtable. And what thynges be thei, that ſhe geueth? Boldnes and Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rednes without feare, quoth he. what be thei? Knowlage, quoth he, to ſuffer nothyng greuouſly in this lyfe. By God, quoth I, theſe bee goodly gyftes: But why ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth ſhe ſo without the
<pb facs="tcp:9631:14"/>
compaſſe? To the intent, quoth he, ſhe may heale thoſe, the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che come thyther, and maketh theim to drincke a pourgacion. Whan they be pourged, from thence ſhee bringeth theim into the vertues. How is this, quoth I? I vnderſtand it not well yet. But thou ſhalt vnderſtande it, quoth he. In lykewyſe as if a man, the whiche is very ſicke, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to a phiſicion, the phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion doth firſt by purgacion ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell all thoſe thynges, that cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the ſicknes: And ſo after re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoreth the pacient to his reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery and helth again. If the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient do not obey to thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, the which the phiſicion co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth he ſhould, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a cauſe he is caſte vp of the
<pb facs="tcp:9631:15"/>
phyſicion, and vndooen by the ſickeneſſe. This I vnderſtand (quoth I.) Euen in the ſame maner, quoth he, it is, whan a man commeth to Learnyng, ſhe cureth hym, and maketh hym drinke hir vertue, firſt to purge hym, and to caſte awaie all the euyls, the whiche he had, whan he came to hir. What be thoſe? Ignoraunce and Errour, the whiche he drancke of Deceyte, and pryde alſo and arrogance, concupiſcence, intemperaunce, furie, couetouſeneſſe, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with whiche he was reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed in the firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe. Then whan he is pourged, whyther doeth ſhe ſende hym? In (quoth he) to knowlage, and to other vertues. To what vertues?
<pb facs="tcp:9631:15"/>
Dooeſt thou not ſee (quoth he) within the gate, a companie of women, the whiche ſeeme to be of good diſpoſicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and well or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, hauyng their apparell not gaie, but ſymple, nor thei be not ſo trymme, nor ſo pickedly atti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as the other be? I ſee them (quoth I) but what be they cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led? The firſt (quoth he) is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Knowlage, the other be hir ſyſters, Strength of minde, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, Goodneſſe, Temperance, So berneſſe, Liberalitee, Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, and Mekeneſſe. O theſe be maruelous goodly, quoth I, In howe great an hope be we nowe? yea if ye vnderſtande, quoth he, and wyll roote in you by practiſe thoſe thynges, the which you heare. we ſhall aſſaie
<pb facs="tcp:9631:16"/>
as diligently as we can, quoth I. Than you ſhall bee ſafe, quoth he.</p>
            <p>Whan theſe women haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued one, whyther dooe they bryng hym? To their mother, quoth he. Who is ſhee? Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citee, quoth he. Who is that? Thou ſeeſt the waie, that goeth vp to that high place, the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is the toppe of all the other compaſſes. I ſee it. There is alſo in the porche a woman of a good grace and fauor, and ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in an high throne, dreſſed gentill womanlyke, and not to trymme, coroned with a veraie faire and flouriſhyng garland? She ſemeth to be ſo. The ſame is Felicitee, quoth he. Whan one commeth thither, what doth
<pb facs="tcp:9631:16"/>
he there? Felicitee, quoth he, with hir power crowneth hym, and ſo doe all the other vertues lykewyſe, as a man the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che hath ouercome marueilouſe great battailes. What battay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les hath he ouercome, quoth I? Very great, quoth he, and great wylde beaſtes, the whiche afore dyd deuour and vexe hym, and made hym their ſlaue, all theſe hath he ouercome, and expelled from hym: and now he is lorde ouer hym ſelfe. Wherfore now they ſerue hym: as he did theim before. I would gladly know, whiche be thoſe wylde beaſtes thou ſpeakeſt of? Firſt, quoth he, Ignoraunce and Deceyte, doe not theſe ſeme to thee wyld beaſtes? ye and very yll wylde
<pb facs="tcp:9631:17"/>
beaſtes (quoth I.) Secondely, Sorowe, wailyng, Couetouſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Intemperance, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther miſchiefe: all thoſe he doeth nowe rule, and is not gouerned nor commaunded by theim, as he was before. O (quoth I) theſe bee goodly actes and dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and a victorie moſte good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: but tell me this, what is the power and vertue of the corone, with the whiche ſhee coroneth hym? It is, yonge man, a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and a myght, that maketh a man welfull. For he that is co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roned with this power and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, is made therby happie and welfull, and hath not the truſt nor hope of his felicitie in other thynges, than in hym ſelfe. O what a goodly victorie telleſt
<pb facs="tcp:9631:17"/>
thou. But whan he is coroned, what doeth he, or whither goeth he? The vertues take hym, and leade hym thyther, whence he came before, and ſhew hym how euyll and how wretchedly they liue, the whiche dwell ſtill there, and in what great daunger and peryll they liue, and howe they erre and wander, and are ledde, as it were by their ennemies: Some by Intemperance, ſome by Pryde, ſome by Couetouſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſome by Vaynglorie, and ſome by other euylles, from the whiche myſchiefes, to whom they were bounde, they can not vnloſe theim ſelfe, to come hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be made whole: but liue in trouble all their lyfe: This they ſuffre, becauſe thei can not
<pb facs="tcp:9631:18"/>
find the waie, that would bring them hyther. For they haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten that that was comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them by Genius.</p>
            <p>Me ſeemeth thou ſaieſt trouth, but yet in this I doubt againe. Why dooe the vertues ſhewe hym the place, from whence he came firſte? He dyd not tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughly knowe (quoth he) nor vnderſtoode any of thoſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, that were there, but he was in doubte. And thorough Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunce and Errour, that he dranke, he eſteemed thoſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to be good, whiche were not good: and thoſe thynges, to be euyll, whiche be not euill: And therfore he him ſelf liued naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily, as the other doe, that there dwell and abide. Now he hath
<pb facs="tcp:9631:18"/>
atteined knowlage of all profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table thynges, he him ſelf liueth well, and dooeth behold other, the whiche liue euyll. Whan he hath looked ouer all, what dooeth he, or whither goeth he? Whither ſo euer he will (quoth he.) For euerie where he is in ſuertee, as he that dwelleth in the denne of Corycus. And whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo euer he goeth, in all thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges he ſhall lyue well, with all ſuertee. And euerie bodie ſhall receiue hym gladly, as the ſicke folkes dooe the phyſicion. But doth not he yet feare thoſe wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, the whiche thou dyddeſt call beaſtes, leſt he ſhould ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſomewhat of theim? No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng at all. He nothyng ſhall be troubled with Sorowe, nor
<pb facs="tcp:9631:19"/>
with Heauineſſe, nor with In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperance, nor with Couetiſe, nor with Pouertee, nor with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other euyll. For he ſhall be lord ouer them all: and be ſafe from all thoſe thynges, the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che before dyd hurte or trouble hym, as they be, that are bitten with a ſerpent called Vipera. For without doubt wylde bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, the whiche hurte all other folke to the death, will not hurt nor trouble theim, for becauſe they haue by this bityng a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie to reſiſt all other: So in lyke wyſe nothyng troubleth this man, becauſe he hath a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie preſent. Me ſeemeth thou ſaieſt verie well: but yet tell me this, what be they, the whiche ſeeme to come yonder from the
<pb facs="tcp:9631:19"/>
hyll? Of the which theſe that be crouned, ſeeme to reioyce and be merie: and thoſe that be vncrou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as it were men in diſpaire, ſeme to knocke their heades and legges: they are alſo withhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by certaine women. Thoſe that be crouned be thei, the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che are made ſafe by learnyng, and they reioyce, that they haue atteyned hir: But thoſe that be vncrouned are they, whiche be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they did diſpayre, came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie from lernyng, made ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by euyll and wretched. but yet thoſe without feare wente to Sufferaunce, and thence tour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned backe again, and erred, and myſſed the waie. But the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that folowe after theim, what be they? Heuineſſe, quoth
<pb facs="tcp:9631:20"/>
he, and Sorowes, and Vexaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Shames, and Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rancies. And it be, as thou ſaiſt, all the euylles in the worlde fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe theim. It is true by Iupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (quoth he) that they folowe theim. Whan theſe folke are come agayne to the firſte com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe, to Luſte and Inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, they do not accuſe them ſelf, but ſtreight they ſpeake e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll bothe of Learnyng, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of them that goe to hir: ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng, that thoſe are wretched, myſerable, and vnhappie, the whiche leauyng the life that thei haue, dooe liue euyll, and haue not the fruicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nor vſe of thoſe good thynges, that they haue. What doe they call good thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges? Riot and Intemperaunce
<pb facs="tcp:9631:20"/>
to ſpeake ſhortely. For, for to eate and drincke lyke beaſtes, they eſteme to be the fruicion of the beſt thynges in this world. But the other women, the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che go thither merie and laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng, what be they called? Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions (quoth he) the whiche af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they haue broughte folke to Lernyng, and that they be gone into the vertues, they goe their wayes to fetche other, and to ſhewe, that thoſe are made hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie and welfull, the which they brought before. But dooe not, quoth I, thoſe opinions com in to the vertues? No (quoth he.) For Opinion may not come in to knowlage: but Opinions delyuer theim that come vnto Learnyng. And whan Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng
<pb facs="tcp:9631:21"/>
hath once receiued theim, then do theſe opinions go backe againe to fetche other, lyke as ſhippes that are dyſcharged of their frought go again and are fylled with other ſtuffe. Theſe thynges me ſeemeth (quoth I) thou haſt very well expouned: but yet thou haſte not declared vnto vs, what Geniꝰ doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand thentrers into lyfe to do. To truſte well and haue good courage (quoth he) and therfore haue ye good corage. For I wil expoune all, and leaue nothyng. Thou ſayeh well (quoth I.)</p>
            <p>¶Then he put forth his hande again. Ye ſee (quoth he) the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, whiche ſemeth to be blind, and to ſtande vpon a rounde ſtone, The whiche I tolde you
<pb facs="tcp:9631:21"/>
euen now, is called Fortune? We ſee hir. Genius comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, quoth he, that folke ſhuld not truſt this woman, nor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue that any thyng, that a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy doth receiue of hir, is either fyrme and ſtable, or maie haue and kepe it ſure and ſafely: nor to eſteme it as his owne. For nothyng can lette hir to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way thoſe thynges againe, and to delyuer theim to ſome other body: And ſhe is wont often ſo to doe. And for this cauſe Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius dooeth commaunde, that hir giftes ſhoulde be littell ſette by: And nother to reioice, whan ſhe geueth theim: nor to be ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, when ſhe taketh them away: and nother to diſprayſe nor to prayſe hir. For ſhe dooeth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng
<pb facs="tcp:9631:22"/>
by reaſon, but all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges raſſhely withoute aduyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and as it happeneth, as I haue tolde you before. For theſe conſideracions he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth, that folke ſhold not eſteme, nor haue in admiracion that, the whiche ſhe doeth. Nor to be lyke the euill marchauntes bankers. For they, whan they haue receiued money of a man, dooe reioyce, and thincke it is their owne: but whan it is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked theim againe, they are myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content, and thinke thei be euill handled, and dooe not remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that they dyd receiue, that that was truſte in their han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, for this intent, that whan ſo euer the owner lyſte, there ſhould bee none obſtacle, but
<pb facs="tcp:9631:22"/>
that he myght take it awaie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. Vnder ſuche maner Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius commaundeth folke not to be affectionate to Fortunes gef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and to remembre, that ſhee hath ſuche a nature to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie and to transferre thoſe thinges ſhe gaue, and by and by again to geue manyfolde thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. Somtyme alſo ſhe dooeth not only take awaie thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ſhee gaue alone, but alſo thoſe thynges that were had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Therefore Genius com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth to take of thoſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ſhe geueth, and he that hath them to goe his waie ſhortly to the ferme and ſure gefte. What gefte is that, (quoth I?) The gefte that folke take of Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, yf they bee made whole
<pb facs="tcp:9631:23"/>
there. Yea and what is that? The true knowlage (quoth he) of profitable thynges, bothe a ſure, and a ſtable, and an immu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>table gefte. Moreouer he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth to flee faſte towarde this knowlage. And whan they come to thoſe women, the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che as I ſaied before, are called Incontinence and pleaſure, he commaundeth them not to truſt thoſe women in any wyſe, nor to tarie till thei come to vntrue Learnyng: There he comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth theim to tarie a whyle and abyde, and to take what ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they wyll of hir, as a helpe or ayde to a further iourneie. Than from thence to goe anon to true Learnyng. Theſe bee the thynges, that Genius com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth.
<pb facs="tcp:9631:23"/>
Who ſo euer beſyde theſe thynges, either dooeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thyng, or miſheareth any thyng, dooeth naught lyke him ſelfe periſhe naughtily.</p>
            <p>¶So now freendes the ſtorie, that is in the table, is ſuche as I haue tolde you. Yet if ye lyſt to enquire of any of theſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges particularly, without diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deigne I ſhall tell it to you.</p>
            <p>Thou ſaieſt well, quoth I. But what doeth Genius commaund theim to take of vntrue Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng? Thoſe thynges that are woorthie &amp; meete to be vſed and occupied. What be thoſe? Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters (quoth he) and other ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the whiche, Plato ſaieth, are to yonge folke in ſteede of a Brydle, to reine them from tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng,
<pb facs="tcp:9631:24"/>
to other thynges. But whether is it neceſſary for a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, if he wyll goe to true Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, to take thoſe thynges or no? Neceſſitee truely, quoth he, there is none. Yet neuertheleſſe they be profitable, but to make folke the better, therto can they nothyng helpe. Thou ſayeſt than, that theſe thynges be not ſo profitable, that by them men maie be made better, for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out theim a bodie maie come to goodneſſe: Yet neuer the leſſe they bee not vnprofytable. If I haue perceyued you well, ye meane this, that without the knowlage of thoſe liberall ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, men maie atteyne to ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and goodnes: in like maner as we may vnderſtand a thyng
<pb facs="tcp:9631:24"/>
ſpoken in a ſtrange language, without the knowlage of that ſame tongue, by a ſpokeſman, that can interprete it vnto vs. Yet neuer the leſſe, it were not vnprofytable for vs, to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand our ſelfe the language, in the whiche it was firſte ſpoken in. Haue not men learned in theſe ſciences, preheminence to be better than other men? How can they excell or haue prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, whan men maie ſee them deceiued in the opinion of good and euyll, as other folke bee: and alſo bounde and tangled with all vngraciouſneſſe? For knowlage of letters, nor vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandyng of other ſciences, doe nothyng let, but that a bodie maie be alſo droncke, intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate,
<pb facs="tcp:9631:25"/>
couetouſe, vniuſte, a tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, and fynallie a foole. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoth a man maie ſee many ſuch. Than how (quoth he) haue thei preheminence, by reſon of thoſe ſciences, to be made the better men? it ſeemeth not by this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. But what (quoth I) is the cauſe? Becauſe (quoth he) they dwell ſtyll in the ſeconde Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe, as it were men approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng toward true Learnyng. And what helpeth that (ꝙ I,) when we maie ſee many times, they come out of the firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe from Inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinence and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vngraciouſnes, to the third compaſſe, to true Learnyng, the whiche dooe paſſe by theſe lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men. And howe can men learned onely in theſe lyberall
<pb facs="tcp:9631:25"/>
ſciences excell other, whan they be more obſtinate, and more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to bee taught, than other folke be? Howe is that (quoth I?) For (quoth he) in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde compaſſe that thyng that they knowe not, they doe feigne theim ſelfe to knowe. If there were none other thyng but this, as long as they haue this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, they muſt needes be vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be ſteered to come to true Learnyng. Moreouer, ſeeſt thou not an other thyng, that the opinions out of the firſte compaſſe, come alſo into them? Wherfore theſe be no whit bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, than thoſe of the firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe: excepte they dooe repent, and be perſwaded that thei haue not the true knowlage, but the
<pb facs="tcp:9631:26"/>
vntrue Lernyng, by whom they be deceyued. And thincke, that as long as they remayne in the contrarie opinion, that thei can neuer be made ſafe and whole. Nor you nother frendes, except you ſo doe, and that theſe ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynges remain ſtedfaſtly in your remembraunce, tyll ſuche tyme as ye haue ingendred in you by practyſe, an habite or cuſtome. Wherfore ye muſt conſyder theſe ſaiynges continually, and not by ſtartes, and thinke all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thynges pertayne nothyng to your pourpoſe. If ye dooe not ſo, of theſe thynges, that ye haue nowe harde, ye ſhall haue no profitte. We ſhall dooe, as ye teache vs: But expoune this vnto vs; Why be not thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:9631:26"/>
thynges, the whiche folke dooe receiue of Fortune, good thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges? as to liue, to be whole, to be riche, to haue glorie, to haue children, to conquere and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and all other thynges like theſe? Or againe, why be not their contraries euyll? For thy ſaiyng ſeemeth to vs incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible, and very farre from our opinion. Come of (quoth he than) and endeuour your ſelfe to aunſwere as ye thynke beſt, to thoſe thynges, the whiche I ſhall aſke you. That ſhall I doe (quoth I.) Than (quoth he) if a body liue euill, is it good to hym to lyue? I thincke no, but rather euill (quoth I.) For how (ꝙ he) can it be good to lyue, whan it is to the liuer euyll?
<pb facs="tcp:9631:27"/>
Certainely (quoth I) to theim, the which liue nought, me thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth lyfe is an euyll thyng: but to theim, the whiche liue well, lyfe is a good thyng. Than (quoth he) thou ſaieſt, that lyfe is bothe a good thyng, and an euyll. Ye truely. Speake not ſo incrediblie and ſo far out of the waie: For it is impoſſible, one thyng to be both good and euyll. For ſo the ſelf ſame thyng ſhould be bothe profitable and noyſome. And one ſelfe thyng alwaies to be woorthie to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, and at the ſame one time alſo to bee eſchewed: me thinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth this farre from reaſon. But howe foloweth it, that though that euill be in him that lyueth euyll, that therfore lyfe
<pb facs="tcp:9631:27"/>
ſelfe ſhould be an euyll thyng? But (quoth he) it is not all one, to liue, and to liue euyll. Doth it not ſeeme alſo ſo to the? Yes. For I dooe not thincke theim both one. Then life ſelfe (quoth he) is not an euill thyng: for if it wer an euill thyng, then thei, the which do liue well, had in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an euill thyng. For thei haue in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> life, the which wer an euil thing. Me ſemeth ye ſay trouth: for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that life hapneth to both, as well to the liuers well, as to the liuers euill. Therfore life can nother be a good thyng, nor an euyll. No more than cuttyng or ſeryng is in them, whiche are diſeaſed, either a ſicke thyng or a whole. Conſider than this, whether had ye leauer to liue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill,
<pb facs="tcp:9631:28"/>
or to die well and nobully? I had rather (quoth I) to die well. Than, to die it is none euyll thyng, ſeeyng that many times death is rather to be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen than lyfe. It is ſo. The ſelfe ſame reaſon maie be made of helth and ſyckenes. For of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten tymes is not profitable to be in health, but the contrarie is to be preferred. Suche cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances there maie be, thou ſaieſt trouth. Come of nowe than let vs conſidre in like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of riches. Maie we not ſee (as it chaunceth often to ſee) a man to haue muche riches, and yet to liue naught and wretched<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly? yea verie many of that ſort. Than ryches helpeth nothyng theſe men to lyue well? It ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
<pb facs="tcp:9631:28"/>
ſo: For they them ſelfe be naught. Than rycheſſe cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not men to bee good, but that dooeth high and perfecte knowlage. Your ſaiyng ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth true. Than by this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon how can richeſſe be a good thyng, whan it helpeth not to make his poſſeſſours to be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Me ſeemeth ye ſaie trouth. And to ſome folke alſo it is not profitable to be ryche, if they knowe not howe to vſe ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſſe. It is true. Howe can that thyng be iudged good of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man, the whiche it is no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitte to haue? It can not.</p>
            <p>Therfore if a man knowe how to vſe rycheſſe well, and as it ſhould be, he ſhall lyue well: If he can not, he ſhall liue naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily.
<pb facs="tcp:9631:29"/>
There can nothyng be tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than this. And for a fynall concluſion, to repute and eſteme theſe thynges, as though they were good thynges, orels reiect or deſpiſe the ſame, as euil thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, is the cauſe, that vexeth or troubleth the moſte part of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: when thei honour theſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaied thynges, and thincke by them onely to obteigne felicitee and welfulneſſe. For, for to get them, they leaue nothyng vndo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, be it neuer ſo vngracious. All theſe thynges they do onely becauſe they knowe not, what is the true goodneſſe.</p>
            <trailer>¶Thus endeth the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Cebes.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:9631:29"/>
            <head>¶How one maie take profite of his enemies.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> PER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue my frend, that thou haſte choaſen a right plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant kynde of liuyng, voyde of buſineſſes of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon welth, wherin neuertheleſſe thou doeſt to the common welth much pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitte: beyng vnto all them that come vnto thee, and eke to them
<pb facs="tcp:9631:30"/>
that kepe thee companie, bothe compenable and pleaſaunt.</p>
            <p>¶But ſence it is ſo, that we maie finde ſome countrey, that wanteth wylde and hurtefull beaſtes, as it is ſaied by Creta: But yet no common welth hath been found, that hath not nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed within it ſelfe, enuie, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deigne, and ſtryfe: of whiche moſte commonly enmitees dooe growe, ye and if there were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng els, frendſhip it ſelfe tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vs to enmitee, whiche the wyſe man Chion perceiuyng, aſked one that vau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted him ſelfe to haue none enmie, if he had alſo no freende. Me thinketh than it were meete for a man of auctoritee, and that medleth in the rule of the common wealth,
<pb facs="tcp:9631:30"/>
that amonge other buſineſſe he ſhoulde haue alſo conſideraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his enemies, and to take good heede, that this was not ſpoken for nought of Xeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon: It is a ſubſtanciall wiſe mans part, to take profytte of his enemies. Therfore I haue gathered together thoſe thinges that came in my mynde now of late, as I reaſoned on this mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tier. And I haue written theim vnto the, in as few wordes, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng hede, as nere as I coulde, that I touche nothyng of thoſe that I wrote afore, in the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptes of good maner, for I ſee that booke oft in thy hande.</p>
            <p>¶To men of the old worlde it ſuffiſed, if they toke no hurt of diuers beaſtes, and in that time
<pb facs="tcp:9631:31"/>
they fought with hurtefull bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes onely for that purpoſe. But they that are of later tyme, fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng the waie how to vſe wilde beaſtes, are not onely not hurt, but alſo they take profitte of theim, feedyng theim with their fleſhe, clothyng them with their flecis, makyng of their mylke and galles, medicines for diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and armyng theim and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendyng them with their ſkyns: in ſo muche that now it is to be doubted, that if beaſtes wanted vnto man, mans lyfe ſhould be but beaſtely, wylde, and nedie. So likewyſe ſence it ſuffyſeth vnto other, to take no hurte of their ennemies: and that Xeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon ſaieth, profite maie be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of ennemies. Belefe is not
<pb facs="tcp:9631:31"/>
to bee taken from ſuche an au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour, but rather the maner and waie muſte be ſought, whereby this profitte maie be gotten by theim, that maie not liue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out enmitees.</p>
            <p>¶The huſbande man can not take from euery tree the wylde nature: nor the hunter can not make euery wylde beaſt gentyll and tame: ſo that the waie hath been found, that for other vſes, both vnfruitfull trees and wild beaſtes haue been profitable.</p>
            <p>¶The Sea water is vnmeete to drinke, and vnpleaſaunt, but it nouriſheth fyſſhes, it carieth vs from place to place, and it ſerueth in bringyng in and bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng out wares.</p>
            <p>¶But Satyrus the firſt tyme
<pb facs="tcp:9631:32"/>
that he ſawe fier, when he wold haue taken it and kyſſed it: Ho, quoth Promotheꝰ, thou rough knaue, if thou take not heede, it wyll make thy lyppes ſmarte: for it burneth, if it be touched, it ſerueth not for that purpoſe: but it geueth light and hete, and is the inſtrument of all craftes, if one can vſe it.</p>
            <p>¶It muſt be ſeene therfore, if alſo an ennemie, that elles were hurtfull and daungerous, maie be touched any other waie, and geue ſom particular vſe of hym ſelfe, and do vs very great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite. For there are many thyngꝭ hateful and greuoꝰ vnto them, to whom thei happen: out of the whiche neuertheleſſe ſome vſe maie be taken. For thou ſeeſt
<pb facs="tcp:9631:32"/>
many vſe ſome diſeaſe of the body, for occaſion of quiet and reſt. Againe, labours and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayles, that haue commen by chance, haue made many mans helth more perfect by exercyſe. Beſides this, there hath beene many, to whom outlawrie and loſſe of money hath bene forde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce to ſtudie and learnyng, as to Diogenes and Crates. And zenon whan he heard that his ſhip was drowned: Thou doeſt very well Fortune (quoth he) in driuyng me to my ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng mantyll.</p>
            <p>¶For like as ſome loue thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, that are good in digeſting, and helefull for the body, if thei eate ſerpentes and ſcorpions, thei digeſt theim: yea and there
<pb facs="tcp:9631:33"/>
are ſome, they are nouryſhed with ſtones and ſhelles, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the force and heate of the ſpirites, that tourne theſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges into nouriſhement: where as theſe, that been tendre and ſickly, can not awaie with bred and wyne. So fooles marre and alſo looſe freendſhips, but they that are wyſe, can profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie vſe enmitees.</p>
            <p>¶Firſt therefore that that in enmitee is moſt hurtfull, ſemeth vnto me to dooe great profitte, if one take heede to it. What is that ſaiſt thou? Truely an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie alwaie watchyng, marketh what thou doeſt, and in ſekyng occaſion of ſclander, prieth and pereth alway on thy liuyng, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing with his ſight like a Lynx,
<pb facs="tcp:9631:33"/>
not onely the tymber, the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng, and the walles of thy houſe, but alſo thy freende, thy ſeruant, and whom ſo euer ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth thee companie, that as nere as he maie, he wyll know what thou dooeſt, pearcyng and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng all thy ſecretes. Where as our freendes by our delaie and negligence, oft tymes are bothe ſicke, and dye withoute our knowlage. And of our enemies well nere we marke their drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes. So that the diſeaſes, the dettes, the ſkoldynges with their wyues, ſhall rather be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whoſe they are, then of their enemies. So chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dooeth be marke fautes, and aboue all thyng, them he ſeketh. Euen like as theſe Grypes, that
<pb facs="tcp:9631:34"/>
Priam and his children mighte be glad to haue had ſuche enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, wherby they toke heede to theim ſelfes, and were renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: truely it ſhall withdrawe, reſtreigne, and leade them from ſuche thynges, that ſhould bee pleaſure and laughter for their enemies.</p>
            <p>¶We ſee alſo theſe muſiciens oft times ſlake &amp; not very hede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, as ofte as they ſyng in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience alone: But if there hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen any dyſdeigne, and ſtryfe with other: than they dooe not only applie their mindes better, but dreſſe their inſtrumentes more diligently, choſe theirſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, tune theim more precyſely, in aſſaiyng often their accorde: So who that perceyueth, that
<pb facs="tcp:9631:34"/>
he hath a diſdeigner, bothe of his name and of his liuyng, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth better hede to hym ſelfe, he examineth all his deedes, and redreſſeth all his lyfe. For of trouthe naughtineſſe hath this propertee, that in offendyng, it feareth more enemies then fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. Therfore Scipio, whan ſome thought Rome to be in a ſuertie, becauſe Carthage was deſtroied, and the Grekes ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come: ye but now (quoth he) we are in greateſt peryll, ſence now we haue none, whom we dreade or feare.</p>
            <p>¶Take with this the anſwere of Diogenes very excellent and mete for a philoſopher: To one that aſked hym, whiche waie he might be reuenged on his enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie:
<pb facs="tcp:9631:35"/>
If thou make (quoth he) thy ſelfe an honeſt and a good man.</p>
            <p>¶Moſt part of men are ſory, whan thei ſee the fayre horſe, or wel praiſed doggꝭ of their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: And againe they are ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, if they ſee theyr lande well houſebanded, or theyr gardeyne fayre and goodly. What tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt thou than they wyll dooe, if thou ſhew thy ſelfe an vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right man, wiſe, good, and thrif<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie, excellent in wel ſaiyng, pure and vncorrupt in mattiers of charge: In temperaunce of thy liuyng, ſobre and meſurable, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng to plow a deepe forow in a wyſe breaſt, whens out dooe ſpryng goodly and fayre coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayles?</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:9631:35"/>¶They that are ouer come, ſaieth Pyndarus, haue their tongue teyed, that thei dare not once hyſce. But that is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliable properly in euery one, that is ouercomen of their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. But in them onely, that ſee them ſelf ouercomen of their ennemies, in diligence, in wyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, in greatneſſe of the mind, in gentylneſſe, and lyberalitee. Theſe thynges dooe folde vp a tonge, as ſaieth Demonſthenes, theſe dooe ſhutte and cloaſe vp the mouth, theſe dooe ſtoppe the throte, theſe cauſe ſylence, theſe cauſe the, that, as ſaith Pynda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, thou darſte not once hyſce. Therefore endeuour thou thy ſelfe, ſence thou maieſt, to ſeeme better then they that be naught.
<pb facs="tcp:9631:36"/>
¶Therfore yf thou deſire to grieue thine ennemie, doe it not this waie, to call hym leude, or dronckerd, knaue, or nygarde, or ſluttiſhe or ſlouen, but rather endeuour thou thy ſelfe to be an honeſt man, endeuour thy ſelfe to be ſobre, and meaſurable, to be true, and to intreate theim gentilly and indifferently, that kepe company and meddle with thee. But if it ſo happen, that thou fall to chidyng and reui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng, take heede, that thou bee clene without thoſe fautes, for whiche thou rebukeſt an other. Retourne thy ſelfe into thyne owne breaſt, looke into thyne owne boſome, and marke well, if there be any thyng fylthie or ſubiecte to vice: Leſt peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb facs="tcp:9631:36"/>
ſome yll tongue haue occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to caſt this in thy teeth: He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>alueth other, and is hym ſelfe full of botches.</p>
            <p>¶But if he call the vnlearned, applie thou thy ſelfe to ſtudie, and quicken thy endeuour: if he call the coward, ſteere thy cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and the readineſſe of thy minde: if he call the vnchaſt and vicious, chaſe out of thy minde the deſire of luſte, if any ſuche printe, vnware to thee, ſticke in thee. For there is nothyng fou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler than ſuche rebuke, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundeth to the rebuker. And there is nothyng more greuous or ſharper. For lyke as the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection of lighte dooeth moſte hurt to ſore eies, ſo doe yll wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, whiche trouthe retourneth
<pb facs="tcp:9631:37"/>
thyther as they came fro.</p>
            <p>¶Truely lyke as the Northe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> wind draweth cloudes toward it, ſo doeth yll liuyng drawe yll ſpeakyng vnto it. Therfore Plato, as ofte as he ſawe anie doe vncomely, to him ſelfe was woonte to ſaie: Am I ſuche in any caſe?</p>
            <p>¶Furthermore, he that hath ſkolded with an other, yf he forthwith behold his owne-life, and redreſſe it, chaungeyng it in to the contrary, and correctyng it: truely he ſhall take great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitte by ſkoldyng, and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe it is bothe taken, and alſo is a veraie foolyſhe thyng. For ſo commonly men are wonte to laughe at hym, that is balde or croked, and blameth an other
<pb facs="tcp:9631:37"/>
for the ſame vyces. But it is moſt of all to be laught at, one to caſt a rebuke to another, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che maie haue ſome rebuke tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to hym ſelfe. As Leo of By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zantia, whan a foule croked fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe caſt vnto hym the ſorenes of his eies: It is natural (quoth he.) But thou dooeſt cary thine owne rebuke vpon thy backe.</p>
            <p>¶Therfore beware that thou caſt not adulterie in ones teeth, if thou vſe a more fylthie fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly luſte: nor attwyte not one of waſte, if thou be a nygard.</p>
            <p>¶Alcmeon laied it to Adra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus, that he was couſine to a woman, that ſlewe hir mother. But what ſaied he againe? He tayed to hym agayne not an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers faute, but his owne, ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng:
<pb facs="tcp:9631:38"/>
Thou ſleweſt thy mother thine owne handes.</p>
            <p>¶Domitius ieſted with Craſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus on this wiſe: Diddeſt thou not weepe, whan thy Lampraie was dead, whiche thou haddeſt kepte in thy ſtewe? But Craſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus retourned the checke on this facion: Didſt thou wepe at all, whan thou buriedſt .iii. wiues?</p>
            <p>¶He that ſhould checke an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, maie not bee a ieſter, or a ſkolder, or a foole: But he muſt be ſuch one, on whom no checke nor faute maie cleue. For it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that god co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded this. (Know thyſelf) to no man more than to him, that ſhould blame and checke an other: Leaſt, if they ſaie what they wyll, they here that that they would not.
<pb facs="tcp:9631:38"/>
For it is wont to be as Sopho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles ſaieth: Whan thou haſte powred out wordes fooliſhlie, and ſaied theim with thy good wyll, againe thou ſhalt here the ſame againſt thy wyll.</p>
            <p>¶And that is the profitte and commoditee, that maie be taken of chidyng with ennemies: and no leſſe profite cometh of the to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that is, if one be yll ſpoken of, and rebuked of his enemies. whervpon it was well and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpoken of Antiſthenes: It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houeth a man for the ſafegarde of his welth and proſperitee, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to haue ſure truſtie frendes, or ſharpe enemies, becauſe they in warning, tother in rebuking, refreigne hym from vyces.</p>
            <p>¶But truely becauſe that now
<pb facs="tcp:9631:39"/>
a daies frendſhip hath loſte hir ſpeche to ſpeake frely, and flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery hath tongue enough, war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng is domme: it remayneth therfore, that we muſt here the trouthe of our ennemies. For lyke as Telephus could not be healed of his wound by no ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of his owne felowes, and was healed by an other wound that Achilles his ennemie gaue hym in the ſame place: ſo they that haue no freendly warner, muſte ſuffer the woordes of an yll willyng enemie, wherby they maie correct and amende their fautes. In whiche tyme the thyng it ſelfe ought to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, and not the mynde of the yll ſpeaker. For lyke as he that thought to haue ſlaine Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theus
<pb facs="tcp:9631:39"/>
of Theſſaly, by chaunce ſtrake ſo a wenne that he had, that he ſaued the man, and by breakyng the wenne ridde hym of the peryll: ſo it is not ſeldom ſeene, that a rebuke caſte out by enmitee and hatered, healeth a ſore of the minde, that was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture vnknowen, orels vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>regarded.</p>
            <p>¶But many that are touched with a rebuke, dooe not conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this, whether they be gyltie of the ſhame that is laied to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but they looke rather, if he that laied it, haue any thyng in him, that maie be caſte againſt hym, And lyke as wraſtelers in the wraſtlyng place, do not bruſſhe away the duſt, but one arayeth an other: ſo with rebukes when
<pb facs="tcp:9631:40"/>
they meete together, one of them ſhameth an other. But it were more accordyng, that he that hath had a checke of his enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, ſhall take that awaie, that is laied againſt him, rather then a ſpotte that one ſheweth hym in his gowne.</p>
            <p>¶Ye and alſo if one laie to thy charge a faut, that thou art not gyltie in, yet it is to be ſought, vpon what cauſes that yl ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng dyd growe: and than it ought to be taken heede of and feared, leſt that vnware we doe any thyng like that, that is lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt vs. As Lacides kyng of Argi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, for his trimme buſhe, and a lyttell more pyked appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raile, was ſklaundered among the common ſort, as tender and
<pb facs="tcp:9631:40"/>
womanniſhe.</p>
            <p>¶The ſame hapned to Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peie, becauſe he ſkratched his head with one finger, although he was farre enough from ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe and wantonneſſe.</p>
            <p>¶So alſo it did happen vnto Craſſus, whiche to by a proper ferme, oft tymes reſorted to a woman of religion, for to wyn hir good wyll.</p>
            <p>¶Truely Poſthumia, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of hir liberall laughyng and talkyng with men, was ſo ſclaundered, that ſhe was accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of adultry, although it was founde, that the faute was not true: Yet the byſhoppe Spuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Minutius at hir departyng warned hir, that ſhe ſhold talke with as great dreade of ſhame,
<pb facs="tcp:9631:41"/>
as ſhe dyd lyue.</p>
            <p>¶And Themiſtocles whan he offended nothyng, yet he gatte by Pauſanias to be ſuſpect of treaſon, becauſe he vſed hym ſo familiarly, and ſent him daiely letters and meſſangers. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whan there is any thyng ſaied agaynſt the, that is not true, thou oughteſt not therfore, becauſe it is falſe, to let it paſſe. But trie with thy ſelfe, if thou haue ſaied or dooen any thyng, or aſſaied any thynge, or if a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monge thy familiars there hath any thing bene, that hath geuen hym prouable occaſion: and if thou fynde it, take heede and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyde it.</p>
            <p>¶Truely if harde happe, that cometh by cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce teacheth ſome,
<pb facs="tcp:9631:41"/>
what is beſt to dooe, as Meto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa ſpeaketh in a plaie: Fortune in takyng away that, that was moſte deere vnto me, hath made me wyſe to my coſt. Why ſhold we not as well vſe our ennemie for a teacher leſſe coſtely, that maie profitte vs, and teacheth vs ſome thyng, that we knewe not afore? For truely manie thynges an ennemie perceyueth better than a freende, becauſe that loue blyndeth in the thyng that is loued, as ſaieth Plato. But vnto hate is ioigned bothe buiſie ſearche and bablyng.</p>
            <p>¶Whan Hieron had his ſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng breth caſte againſt hym of his ennemie, he came home and chode his wyfe, ſaiyng: Why diddeſt not thou ſhewe me this
<pb facs="tcp:9631:42"/>
faute? But ſhe that was chaſt and ſymple, aunſwered: I had wente (quoth ſhe) that all men had ſauoured on the ſame fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. So that, whiche maie be ſenſiblely perceiued, and thoſe thynges that bee in the bodie ſeene of euery man, thou ſhalte ſooner knowe theim of thine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, than of thy freendes or felowes.</p>
            <p>¶Put to this, that where it is no ſmall part of vertue to haue a ſobre tongue, alwaies obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to reaſon: that thou canſte not haue, without thou by mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che exercyſe, heede, and ſtudie, ſubdue the yll mocions of thy mynde, of whiche ſorte angre is one. For as from fooles woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des dooe ſkape out, and as Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mere
<pb facs="tcp:9631:42"/>
ſaieth: The fleeyng voice forſaketh the cloaſure of the mouth. So it is moſte wont to happen to vnexercyſed mindes, that ſlyppe and ſlide, by vnmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate anger, by vntemperate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of mynde, and by ſmall heede of liuyng.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, as ſaieth the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Plato, the lighteſt thyng that is, bothe god and man puniſhe with greatteſt peyne. But a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſyde, ſylence, where as it is alwaie gyltleſſe, and not onely not hurtfull, it hath beſydes in chidyng, a ſauour of Socrates conſtance, or of Hercules force rather, for he alſo toke leſſe hede of greuous wordes, then he did of flies.</p>
            <p>Surely where as there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb facs="tcp:9631:43"/>
more graue or fairer, than whan thy ennemy chydeth, to holde thy peace, as one that ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth by a greatte rocke, ſo alſo doeth ſuche an exercyſe ſpread further. For if thou vſe to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre thyne enemies chidyng, hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng thy peace, thou ſhalt verie eaſely ſuffre thy wyues ſcol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng, whan ſhe is angry, and beare without trouble the cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng of thy frende, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre of thy brother. For of thy father and thy mother thou wilt ſuffre knockes and ſtrokes, and be not moued with angre.</p>
            <p>¶And Socrates dydde ſuffre Xantippa his wyfe at home to chyde and combre him, the more eaſely to kepe company with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if he vſed to forbeare hir.
<pb facs="tcp:9631:43"/>
But it is muche better in beyng exerciſed with checkes, rebukes, and hatredes of enemies, to vſe to ſubdue anger, &amp; not to chafe whan thou art yll ſpoken to.</p>
            <p>Therefore on this wyſe one ought to vſe ſobreneſſe and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feraunce in enmitees. But ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleneſſe, great mynde, and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tylneſſe is more accordyng in freendſhips. For it is not ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt to deſerue well of a freend, as it is ſhame not to dooe it, as ofte as neede requireth. But yet it is taken for gentylneſſe, when chaunce geueth occaſion, to let paſſe and not to be reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged on thyne ennemie.</p>
            <p>¶But he that receiueth not his good wyll, and praiſeth not his gentilnes, that ſoroweth the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
<pb facs="tcp:9631:44"/>
of his enemie, and helpeth hym, if he deſyre it, and taketh ſome heede to his children, or to his houſe, that is in peril, truly he hath an hert of a diamant, or els of yron.</p>
            <p>¶Whan Ceſar had comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the images of Pompei, that were caſt downe, to be ſette vp againe: Thou haſt (quoth M. Tullius) ſet vp Pompeis ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and ſtabliſhed thine owne. Wherfore an enemie is not to be diſpraiſed, nor to be deceiued of his honour, whiche is to be praiſed, and woorthy, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a greatter preyſe theron cometh vnto theim that ſo doe praiſe. Beſide that, he that prei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth one, that deſerueth it, is better beleued, whan he bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth,
<pb facs="tcp:9631:44"/>
as one that hateth not the man, but that aloweth not his deede.</p>
            <p>¶And that that is moſt godly of all, and moſt profitable, he ſhall in no wiſe enuy his fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate frendes, nor his familiars, whan thei doe any thyng praiſe woorthie, who ſo euer vſeth to praiſe his ennemies, and not to gnawe nor byte at their good fortunes. Is there any thyng that bredeth ſuche profite in vs, or that ingendreth in our myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des a better vſe, than that that taketh from vs dyſdeigne and enuie? For as in a common wealth there are many thynges neceſſarie and yet naught, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſence they bee comen in cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, and gotten the ſtrengthes
<pb facs="tcp:9631:45"/>
of a law, yet ſhall thei, to whom they be hurtfull or greuous, not lyghtlie dooe theim awaie: So enmitee bringeth with it many vyces, as angre, ſuſpection, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioiſyng of others harm, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of wronges, and leaueth the printes of theſe in the mind.</p>
            <p>¶Beſides that many thynges, whiche if thou do them to thine ennemie, ſeeme neyther yll nor wrongefull, ſo remaine they in vs, that ſkant they can be put awaie, as is craftineſſe, deceite, and ſubtyltees. Whereby oft tymes by the cuſtome, we ſhall vſe theim to our freendes, if we be not ware howe to vſe theim to our enemies. Therfore Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagoras commaunded veraie well, whan he moued men from
<pb facs="tcp:9631:45"/>
takyng of fowle, and of fiſſhe, and forbadde the killyng of all gentyll beaſtes, to the ende that in beaſtes we ſhould vſe to tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per our ſelfes from crueltee and rauenyng. But it is muche more goodly, in beeyng a gentyll, a iuſt, and ſymple ennemie, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates and ſtryfes againſt men, to chaſtiſe the foule and deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full affections of the minde, and to ſubdue them, to the ende that in medlyng with freendes men maie vtterly forbeare them.</p>
            <p>¶Scaurꝰ was at debate with Domitius, and ſewed hym: ſo a ſeruaunt of Domitius, afore the mattier was pleaded, came vnto Scaurus, and aduertiſed hym, that he had a ſecrete thyng to tell hym: but he would not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre
<pb facs="tcp:9631:46"/>
the felow to ſpeake, but toke him and ſent him to his maſter.</p>
            <p>¶Cato, whan Murena dyd ſewe hym, and ſought together argumentes of the accuſacion, there folowed hym (as was the cuſtome) they that awayted, what ſhould be dooen, and thee ofte tymes woulde aſke hym, if that daie he woulde dooe any thyng, that myght perteyne to his accuſyng: and if he denyed it, they beleued hym and wente their waie. And truly that was a great token, that they had a good opinion of Cato.</p>
            <p>¶But this is the faireſt of all, that once when we are accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to doe vprightly and iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with our ennemies, we ſhall neuer meddle deceitfully or falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:9631:46"/>
with our freendes and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liars. But becauſe it muſte ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des be, that euerye kocke haue his combe, and euery mynde of man of him ſelfe bredeth ſtryfe, ſuſpect, and enuie: it were not vnprofitable, among freendes that haue but holow mindes, as ſaieth Pyndarus, if a manne poure out the purgyng of ſuche fautes vpon his ennemies, and to leat it renne as into a ſynke, farre of from his frendes or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliars. Whiche me thincketh Onomademus an honeſt man perceiued, whiche was in Chio, whan there was a mutenyng there, on that part that had the better, and warned them of his ſyde, not to chaſe them all out, that were of the contrary ſyde,
<pb facs="tcp:9631:47"/>
leſt (quoth he) that we begynne to fall out with our frendes, if we wante enmies. And if thoſe vyces on this wyſe ſhould bee conſumed on enmies, they ſhall the leſſe greue freendes.</p>
            <p>¶For truely the potter ſhould not enuie the potter, nor the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger the ſynger, as Heſiodus ſaieth: and it is not meete, that a man ſhould diſdein his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, or his coſyn, or his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if he waxe riche, and haue good fortune. But if there be none other waie to rydde thy ſelfe from ſtrife, enuie and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deigne, than vſe thy ſelfe to be ſorie for thyne ennemies good fortune, and ſharpen the edge of anger againſt theim. For as theſe connyng gardiners thinke
<pb facs="tcp:9631:47"/>
to make roſes and violettes the better, if thei ſow oynions and garlyke nere by them, that what ſo euer ſower ſauour be in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it maie bee purged in to the to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: ſo an ennemie receiuyng into hym, our enuy and waie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardnes, ſhall make vs better and leſſe greuous to our fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, that haue good fortune.</p>
            <p>Wherfore agaynſt theim muſt be exerciſed the ſtryfe of glory, of rule, and of good gaynyng, but not ſo muche, that we ſhuld tourment our ſelfe, though they haue more thanne we: But to marke al thinges by what mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes they paſſe vs, and lette vs endeuour vs to paſſe theim in diligence, endeuour, ſobreneſſe, and warenes: As Themiſtocles
<pb facs="tcp:9631:48"/>
was wont to ſaie, that he could not ſlepe for Myltiades victory at Maratho.</p>
            <p>¶For he that is brought to ſo lowe mynde, and faintyng for enuie, becauſe he thinketh hym ſelf paſſed of his enemie, in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernaunce, or in obteignyng of cauſes, or in fauour, or aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritee with frendes, or with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men, and not rather ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoureth and aſſaieth ſomething in deſpite of hym, truely he is holden with a foolyſhe and a vayne enuie. But he whom hate blyndeth not ſo, but that he maie iudge him, whom he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, and alſo maie looke with indifferent eies, both vpon his life, and his maners, his woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and his deedes: of a ſuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb facs="tcp:9631:48"/>
he ſhall perceiue manie of thoſe thynges, that he enuyeth, to come vnto the tother by dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, prouiſion, and of deedes well dooen. And therewithall by exerciſe ſharpyng the takyng heede of paſſyng hym, and the ſtudie of honour, he ſhall ſhake of all idilneſſe and falſe herte. So that if we ſee that thei haue gotten in the court or in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwelth, any vnhoneſt or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſerued power, either by flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie, or by deceipte, or by falſe iudgement, or by mede, it ſhall not be greuous vnto vs, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pleaſure, in laiyng together our vpright liuyng with their naughtineſſe. For truely all the golde that is eyther aboue the earth or vnder the earth, is not
<pb facs="tcp:9631:49"/>
to be compared with vertue, as ſaieth Plato. It is meete alſo to haue alwaie in remembrance that woorde of Solon: We wyll not ſaieth he, chaunge the richeſſe of vertue, neither for the largeſſe that is cried by a great nombre, hyred for meat, nor for honours, nor for the chefe place among the wyues and concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines of dukes and princes. For there is nothyng to be wondred at, or notable, that groweth of diſhoneſtee. But the louer is blinde in that that he loueth, as ſaieth Plato, and better we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue if our ennemies dooe any thyng vncomely. Yet maie we not, though they dooe naughti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take an vnprofitable glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or and if they doe well, be
<pb facs="tcp:9631:49"/>
moued with an idell griefe, but in eche of this is to be thought, that in beeyng ware of the tone we maie be letter then they, and folowyng the tother, that we be no woorſe.</p>
            <trailer>¶Thus endeth Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarche to take profite of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:9631:50"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>The maner to chooſe and cheriſhe a freende.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O fil vp the padges, that elles wolde haue been voyde, I thoughte it ſhold no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hurte nor diſpleaſe, to adde herevnto a fewe ſaiynges, howe a man ſhoulde chooſe and cheriſhe a freend. Cicero ſaieth, that Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio complayned greatly, that men were more diligent in all thynges, than in freendſhippe: euery man knoweth how manie
<pb facs="tcp:9631:50"/>
gotes and ſhepe he hath, but no man can tell howe many freen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des he hath: And in the gettyng of other thynges, men vſe great care and diligence, but in choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng of freendes they be veraie negligent, nor they haue not as it were markes and tokens, by the whiche they maie deme thoſe that are feete to be receiued into freendeſhip. The booke ſaieth, haue not frendſhip with an yre full man, nor with a foole: but as Cicero ſaith, men firme, and ſtable, and conſtaunt, ſhould be taken into freendeſhip. Of the whiche ſorte is great ſcarſitee and lacke, and to iudge whiche they bee, is a very harde thyng, excepte we make a profe, and we can not make a profe therof
<pb facs="tcp:9631:51"/>
till we be entred into frendſhip. So, freendſhippe goeth before iudgement.</p>
            <p>¶Some there be, that a ſmall ſumme of money ſhal ſhew how ſure freendes they bee. Some there are, whiche a littell thyng can not remoue, and yet they be knowen in a great neede.</p>
            <p>¶And if we happe to fynde a freende, that deemeth it a foule and a ſhamefull thyng to ſette more by money than by freend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, yet where ſhall we fynde them, that will not more eſteme honours, rowmes, lordſhippes, powers, and abundaunce of ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſſe, than freendſhip? But as the ſame Cicero ſaieth, nother profites, honours, riches, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, nor none other ſuche like
<pb facs="tcp:9631:51"/>
thynges, ſhould be more ſet by than frendſhip. But yet he that is a good man, ſhall dooe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng for his frendes ſake, that is eyther againſte the common welth, or els againſt his othe or fidelitee. For the offence is not excuſable, to ſaie, thou dyddeſt it for thy frendes ſake. And yet the ſame Cicero, as Gellius do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth recite his woordes, ſaieth, that where our freend ſtandeth in ieopardie, either of his lyfe or of his good renoume, we maie ſomewhat ſwarue aſyde out of the waie. But in other places he expoundeth him ſelf ſhewyng plainely, that we ſhould require nothyng of our freend, but that that is honeſt.</p>
            <p>¶And nowe concernyng the
<pb facs="tcp:9631:52"/>
truſt that we ought to haue the our freend, Seneca ſaieth: He that eſtemeth any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his frend, the whiche he can not truſte ſo muche as hym ſelfe, dooeth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue hym ſelfe. And he that maketh and proueth his freend with feaſtyng at the table, doth fayle. It is vertue, ſaieth Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero, the whiche both wynneth and entertaineth freendes. A man ſhoulde reaſon and debate all thynges with his freend, but firſt he ſhoulde debate and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon with hym, whether he bee a freend or no. No man needeth to miſtruſt freendſhyp, but firſt lear hym examyne and deeme, whether it be freendſhip or not. ¶They dooe agaynſt the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptes of Theophraſt, the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che
<pb facs="tcp:9631:52"/>
loue before they iudge, and not after thei haue demed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> thou ſhouldeſt a longe time conſidre, whether thou ſhuldeſt take any into thy frendſhip: and whan it liketh the ſo to do, than receiue him with al thy very hert, &amp; talk as boldly with hym, as though thou were alone. But yet lyue thou after ſuch facio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that thou co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit nothyng to hym, but that thou woldeſt commyt to an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie. But for becauſe ther be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine buſineſſes, the whiche cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome maketh ſecrete, make thy frend priuy to all thy cares and thoughtes. Thou ſhalt do thus if thou ſuppoſe hym to be ſure &amp; faithfull. For many ſhew the maner &amp; waie to deceiue, while they feare to be deceiued. And
<pb facs="tcp:9631:53"/>
ſome tell theim that they meete by the waie, and blowe in euery mans eare, it that ſhold only be opened and ſhewed to frendes. Again, ſome alſo dreade ſo mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the conſcience of their moſte dere freendes, that if they maie, they wyll kepe cloſe within the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all their ſecretes, becauſe they wyll not put theim in truſt ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. None of theſe two waies is to be taken, for eche of theim bothe is naught, to truſte euery body, and to truſte no man. Of whiche two fautes the firſte is the more honeſt, and the other the more ſure. And though the wyſe man be content with hym ſelfe, yet wyll he haue a freend, and it be for none other cauſe, but to exerciſe freendſhippe, leſt
<pb facs="tcp:9631:53"/>
ſo great a vertue ſhould lye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyde. Not for that that Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure ſaieth, that he maie haue one to tende hym whan he is ſicke, or els that maie ſuccour hym, if he be caſte in priſon, or be poore and nedie, but that he maie haue one, whom ſicke and diſeaſed he may tend vpon, and whom he maie delyuer oute of warde, if he happe to come in his ennemies handes. He that regardeth him ſelfe, and for his owne ſake ſeeketh frendſhyp, he intendeth euyll: and lyke as he beginneth, ſo ſhall he ende. He thincketh he hath got a freende to helpe him out of priſon, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che whan he heareth the chaines rattell, goeth his waie. Theſe freendeſhyppes, as the people
<pb facs="tcp:9631:54"/>
ſaieth, dure for a tyme. He that is receiued into freendeſhip for loue of profitte, as longe as he is profitable, he pleaſeth. It is nedeful that the beginnyng and endyng of freendſhippe, ſhould agree. He that beginneth to be a freend, becauſe it is expedient for hym, ſome price ſhall pleaſe hym againſt freendſhip, if there bee anie pryce in it, that maie pleaſe hym aboue freendeſhyp. Thou ſaieſt: To what intent ſhould I prepare a freende? I anſwere, that thou maieſt haue one, whom thou maieſt accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, whan he is baniſhed, for whom thou maieſt put thy ſelfe in daunger of death. For the tother is rather a chapmanſhip than a frendſhip, whiche hath a
<pb facs="tcp:9631:54"/>
reſpecte to profitte, and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth, what auayle he maie get therby. There is nothyng, that ſo muche deliteth the mynde, as faithfull freendſhip. And he is well happie, that fyndeth a true freende, ſaieth the booke. O howe great is the goodneſſe, whan the breaſtes be prepared readie, into the whiche all ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretes maie ſurely be powred, whoſe conſcience thou dreadeſt leſſe than thyne owne, whoſe talkyng eaſeth the grefe and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uineſſe of thy hert, the ſentence geueth readie and quicke coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle, the cheere daſſheth the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde ſorowe, and the very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard and beholdyng delyteth? And becauſe the vſe of freende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is variable and manifold,
<pb facs="tcp:9631:55"/>
and there be many cauſes geuen of ſuſpection and offence, the whiche is a wyſe mannes parte to eſchue, to helpe, and to ſuffre. Frendes muſt oft be moniſhed, and rebuked, and that muſte be taken freendly, whan it is doen of good wyll. But for ſo mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che as Terence ſaieth, Trouthe bredeth hate, whiche is as a poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to freendſhip, we muſt take heede, that our monicion be not ſowre, and that the rebuke be without vyle wordes. For vyle rebukes, as the booke ſaieth, fordoeth freendſhip.</p>
            <trailer>¶Thus endeth the maner to chooſe and cheriſhe a freende.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:9631:55"/>
            <head>A comfortable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortacion againſt the chances of death, made by Eraſmus Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terodamus.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Owe bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter &amp; howe greuouſe a wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth youre Fatherlye hert for the deathe of your moſt goodly child, I light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly coniect by mine owne ſorow. And therfore I were right mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che vncourtoys, if that I in ſo ſorowful a chance wold warne you his father to make lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion,
<pb facs="tcp:9631:56"/>
whan I that am but a ſtraunger can not chooſe but weepe and wayle. Ye mighte well thincke me rude and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taught, if I would goe aboute to heale your grefe, whan I my ſelfe had nede of a phiſicion: if I woulde leat you his father to weepe, whan the teares ſtyll a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly trykell downe from myne eien. And all be it, that the ylke ſtroke of fortune ought deeper to pearce your fatherly breaſt: yet your great wiſedome was wont ſo to rule you (in all your deedes) that ye not onely with a ſtrong and a ſlout mind, but alſo with a glad and a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry chere, would ſuffre and paſſe ouer all ſuche chaunces as hap to mankynde. Wherefore ye
<pb facs="tcp:9631:56"/>
ought ſo to ſettel your ſelf, that if ye can not as yet put awaie cleane the ſorowe of your herte (for no man can denie but that ye haue right good cauſe to bee heauy) yet at the leaſt wiſe ſome what ſuppreſſe and moderate the ſame dolour. And for what cauſe ſhould ye not cleane for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geat it? Seeyng that the ſpace of a fewe daies wyll cauſe ide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ottes ſo to do, me thinketh rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhould perſwade an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent wyſe man. For what ſeelie mother dooeth ſo extremely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile the death of hir child, but that in ſhorte ſpace of tyme hir ſorow ſomwhat aſſlaketh, and at length is cleane forgotten? To haue alway a ſtedfaſt mind is a token of a perfecte wyſe
<pb facs="tcp:9631:57"/>
man. But for thoſe chaunces, vnto the whiche we all equally (both more and leſſe) be ſubiect to ſorow out of meaſure, me thinketh it extreme foolyſhnes. For who is not ware (except he that myndeth nothyng) that he is borne vnder ſuche a condici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that whan ſo euer god wyll call hym: he muſt foorth with nedes depart hence? So than what other thyng (I pray you) dooeth he, that bewayleth ones death, than lamentably com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playne, that he is mortall? Or why ſhoulde we rather ſorow the departyng hence, than the entryng into this worlde, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyderyng that bothe ar equally naturall? Euen in like caſe as though one ſhoulde geue great
<pb facs="tcp:9631:57"/>
thanckes for to bee called to a great feaſt or dyner, and would lamente and demeane great ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe, whan he ſhould departe awaie thence.</p>
            <p>¶If that a manne, as it were from an high lookyng place, wold aduiſe well the condicion and life of all mankind: might he not well recken hym ſelfe a nyce felow, if he among ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfolde exaumples of priuaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and among ſo thicke buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als of yonge and old, would be greuouſely vexed in his mynde, as though vnto him onely were chaunced ſome newe and great euyll: and as though he onely beyng happie aboue other, wold deſire and looke to ſtand with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the common lot? For whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the
<pb facs="tcp:9631:58"/>
conſideracion the excellent wiſe men that found and made lawes in old tyme, to the entent that they wolde ſome what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clyne to the affections of paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and to the ende they woulde not be ſeene to exclude euery bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy from that paſſion, beyng al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo condemned of ſome of the ſtoicke philoſophers: they ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytted vnto theim a certayne tyme to mourne, the whiche en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured not very longe: Eyther becauſe that they well vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode and knew, that in thoſe maner of chaunces, the whiche are both commune to al folkes, and alſo dooe not hap through any iniurie of Fortune, but are induced by the very courſe and ordynance of Nature, ſhorte
<pb facs="tcp:9631:58"/>
mournyng ſhould ſuffice: yea vnto theim that were not able to moderate all affections: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideryng that Natures ſelfe by littell and littell ſoupleth the wound that ſhe made, and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth awaie the ſcarre: Or elles becauſe they diligently marked, that mournyng was not onely vnprofytable vnto theim that were bemoned, but alſo hurtful to theim that made ſuche mone, and greuouſe and vnquiette to their freendes, acquaintaunce, and companie.</p>
            <p>¶But nowe yf a man would conſider the matter a right, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it not ſeme a poinct of mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, willyngly of one harme to make twayne, and whan ye can not by no maner reaſon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer
<pb facs="tcp:9631:59"/>
your predeſtinate loſſe, yet wilfully to annoy and hurte your owne ſelfe? In lyke ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as though a man that his enemies hath ſpoyled of part of his goodes, wolde in his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger throw all that euer remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into the ſee: and than wold ſaie, how he by that meane dyd bewayle his loſſe.</p>
            <p>¶If we wyll regarde the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Mimus, whoſe ſaiyng may beſeeme any Phyloſophier to ſpeake: Thou muſt paciently ſuffre, and grutch not at it that can not be amended: Let vs cal to mynde the muche goodly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aumple of the ryght excellent kyng Dauid, the which ſo ſone as tidynges was brought hym, that his ſonne, that he ſo tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:9631:59"/>
loued, was dead: he foorth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with roſe vp from the grounde, and ſhaked and bruſſhed of the duſte, he threwe awaie his ſhert of heare, and ſo whan he had waſſhed and annoincted, with a glad countenaunce and a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry chere he wente to dyner. And becauſe his freendes marueyled thereat, he ſaied to theim: For what entent ſhould I kyll my ſelfe with wo and ſorowe? For vnto this tyme ſome hope I had, that god being moued with my lamentacion, would haue ſaued my childe a liue: but now all our weepyng teares can not reſtore hym againe to vs alyue: we ſhall ſhortely ſpede vs hence after hym. Who is ſo fonde to crouche and pray him, whom
<pb facs="tcp:9631:60"/>
he knoweth wel, wyll incline to no praiers? There in nothyng more vntreatable than death, nothyng is more deffe, nor no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng more rigorous. By craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie handling the ſauage beaſtes, yea the moſt wyld of theim all, are made tame: There is a waie to breake the harde Marbull ſtone: and a meane to mollifie the diamante: but there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng, wherwith death wyll be appeaſed or ouercome. It nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpareth beautie, riches, age, nor dignitee. And therefore it ought to greue vs muche the leſſe, eyther becauſe it can not be eſchewed, or els becauſe it is equally commune to vs all.</p>
            <p>¶What needeth me to goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute to reherſe to you here the
<pb facs="tcp:9631:60"/>
manifolde examples of the gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyles, the whiche with a noble and a conſtaunt courage toke well in worth the death of their dere frendes? In whiche con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauntnes of mynde, is it not a great rebuke for vs that be chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiens, to be of theim ouer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men? Call nowe to your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce thilke ſaiyng (well woorthy to be enrolled in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng) of Telamon and Anaxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras: I wiſt well I begotte a mortall creature.</p>
            <p>¶Thynke vpon Pericles the Duke of Athenes, the whiche is no leſſe renowmed for his elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, than he is for his force and manlynes: all be it that he within .iiii. daies ſpace loſt his ii. ſonnes, that were endewed
<pb facs="tcp:9631:61"/>
with right noble qualitees, he not onely neuer chaunged his chere, but alſo he, beyng crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned (as was the guyſe than) ſpake and reaſoned among the people of mattiers concernyng their common wealth.</p>
            <p>¶Haue in mynde alſo Xeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon the worthie ſcoler of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates: to whom tidynges was brought as he was doyng ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, that his ſonne was deade: he made no more to doe but put of his crowne, and foorthwith dyd put it on againe, as ſoone as he vnderſtode that his ſonne was manly ſlayne in battayle. ¶Remembre Dion of Syra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, the whiche on a tyme (as he was ſecretely talkyng with his freendes) ſodainely heard a
<pb facs="tcp:9631:61"/>
great noiſe and rumbling in his houſe: And whan he had enque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red what the mattier ment, and was enfourmed that his ſonne had fallen from on hygh, and was deade: he beyng therwith nothyng amoued, commaunded the corps (as the maner was) to be deliuered to women to bury. For he ſaied, he wold not leaue of his pretenſed pourpoſe for that mattier.</p>
            <p>¶Whom Demoſthenes folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing, the .vii. daie after the deth of his onely and moſte entierly beloued daughter, beyng crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and araied in a fayre white garment, he came foorth abrode amonge the people. Of whiche deede the accuſacion of his foe Aeſchynes, both confirmeth the
<pb facs="tcp:9631:62"/>
trouth, &amp; ſetteth out the glorie. ¶Thinke alſo vpon the kyng Antigonus, the whiche when he heard tidynges, that his owne ſonne was ſlain in a diſordred ſkyrmiſſhe: pauſyng a littell, and beholdyng theim well that brought him the tidynges, with a ſtoute and a conſtante mynde he ſaied: O Alcynonen (that was his ſons name) all to late thou periſheſt, that wouldeſt ſo fooliſhely caſte thy ſelfe awaie among thy fooes, nothyng re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardyng thine owne health nor my monicions and woordes.</p>
            <p>¶If ye delite more to heare the examples of Romains, beholde Puluillꝰ Horace, to whom (as he was dedicatyng the capitol) tidynges was broughte, that
<pb facs="tcp:9631:62"/>
his ſonne was dead: he neyther drew away his hande from the poſte, nor tourned not his chere from religion to priuate ſorow. ¶Conſydre how Paulus Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milius, whan he had within the ſpace of .vii. daies loſt his .ii. ſonnes, he came foorth abrode amonge the people of Rome, and there ſhewed theim, that he was very glad, that by the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentacion of his houſeholde (whiche was but a priuate ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row) he had redeemed the enuie of Fortune bent toward the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al. ¶Thinke alſo how Q. Fabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Maximus (whan he was conſull) and had loſt his ſonne, that was than a man in hygh rowme and dignitee, and great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly renowned for his noble a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctes
<pb facs="tcp:9631:63"/>
he came foorth abroade a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the people gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and there to theim he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited the commendacion of his ſonne.</p>
            <p>¶Thinke on alſo whan Cato Cenſorius his eldeſt ſonne died, the whiche was a yonge manne of ſingular witte and high pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſſe, and therto elect and cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to be Mayer: yet was he nothyng ſo amoued with that chaunce, that he would in any thyng more ſlackely endeuour hym ſelfe about the needes and buſineſſe of the common welth. ¶Ye ſhould remembre Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius, whoſe ſurname wasking, whan his ſonne of right noble diſpoſicion, and that ſtode high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the fauour and good opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb facs="tcp:9631:63"/>
of the people, and therto beyng his onely ſon, was dead, he toke the loſſe of hym with ſo conſtaunt a minde, that foorth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with euen from the buryall of hym he cauſed the Senatours to aſſemble together to ordeyne lawes concernyng theyr com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon welth.</p>
            <p>¶Ye ſhould not forget Lucius Sylla, whoſe valiant and moſt fierce courage toward his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, the death of his ſon could nothyng abate, nor cauſe that he ſhould ſeeme falſely to haue vſurped or taken vpon hym to be called by this ſurname felix, that is to ſaie, lucky or welthy. ¶Whan Caius Caeſar (that was Sylla his felow in row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth) had inuaded Britaine,
<pb facs="tcp:9631:64"/>
and hadde tidynges that his daughter was dead: yet er thre daies were fully ended, he went about his impery all buiſineſſe. ¶Whan Marcus Craſſus (in the warre that he made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Parthiens) behelde his ſonnes head, the whiche his ennemies in ſkorne and deriſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on had ſet vpon a moriſpykes end, and the more to exaſperate and augment his calamitee, thei approached neere to his armie, and with woordes of reproche and blame, they ſhewed it vp: he tooke in woorth all that do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng with ſo conſtant a mynde, that ſodainely he rode forby all his battailes, and ſaid to them with a lowde voyce, that that was his own priuate harm, but
<pb facs="tcp:9631:64"/>
the health and ſaluacion of the common weale ſtode in the ſaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of them his men of warre. ¶But nowe to ouerpaſſe the manifolde examples of Galba, Pyſo, Scaeuola, Metellus, Scaurus, Marcellus, and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidius: remembre whan Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius Caeſar had loſt him, whom he bothe begotte, and moſte en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tierly loued: yet for all that he (his owne ſelfe) in the common pulpit lauded and prayſed his ſonne, the corps beyng preſent, all onely couered with a littell veyle: and whan all the people of Rome wepte and bewayled his ſonnes death, he his father wept not a teare.</p>
            <p>¶And ſuerly lyke as it is a right goodly thyng to folowe
<pb facs="tcp:9631:65"/>
and dooe as theſe men dyd: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo were it a right ſhamefull thyng, if menne ſhould not be found as ſtedfaſt and as ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly minded as women haue been in ſuche caſe.</p>
            <p>¶Cornelia ſawe and hehelde hir two ſonnes (Titus Graccꝰ, and Caius Graccus) ſlain and vnburied: and whan hir freen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des comforted hir and ſaied, ſhe had a wretched chaunce: I will neuer ſaie (quoth ſhe) that I am vnluckie or vnfortunate, that haue borne ſuche two children. ¶But whereto dooe we nowe repete theſe examples out of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient chronicles: as though we ſawe not daiely before our face ſufficient exaumples? Beholde your neighbours, beholde your
<pb facs="tcp:9631:65"/>
kynſfolke and alies: howe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, yea ſeely women, ſhall ye finde, the whiche veraie mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately take in good woorth the death of their children? This mattier is ſo plaine, that there nedeth no great helpe of philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophie therto. For he that wold conſider well in his minde, how wretched on all ſydes this our lyfe is, to howe many perils, to howe many ſickeneſſes, to how many chaunces, to howe many cares, to howe many incommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditees, to how many vices, and to howe many iniuries it is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered: how littell and how ſmall a porcion therof we paſſe foorth (I will not ſaie in plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure) that is not attached with ſome maner griefe and diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure?
<pb facs="tcp:9631:66"/>
and than further to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider howe ſwiftly it vaniſheth and rolleth awaie, that we maie in maner reioyce and be glad of them that been departed out of this world in their youth.</p>
            <p>¶The ſhortnes of our life Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ripides ſadly expreſſeth, whiche calleth the lyfe of mortall crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures one littell daie. But Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lereus Demetrius doeth better, whiche correctyng the ſaiyng of Euripides ſaieth, that the lyfe of man ſhould rather be called the Minute of an howre. But Pyndarus ſayeth beſt of all, whiche calleth the lyfe of man the dreame of a ſhaddowe. He ioigneth twoo ſpeciall thynges of nothyng together, to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that he would declare how
<pb facs="tcp:9631:66"/>
vaine a thyng this lyfe is.</p>
            <p>Now how wretched and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable the ſame life is on euery behalfe, the auncient poetes ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to perceiue it paſſyng well: the whiche deemed, that a man coude not more truely nor more better name mortall creatures, than ſurname theim veraie my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable wretches. For the firſt age or formoſte parte of mans lyfe (the whiche is reckened the beſt) is ignorant: The middell parte of the life is aſſailed with trouble and care of manyfolde buſineſſes: and yet al this while I ſpeake but of theim that bee moſte luckie and fortunate.</p>
            <p>Therfore who is he, whiche of veraie right will not approue the ſaiyng of Silenus: the beſt
<pb facs="tcp:9631:67"/>
is neuer to be borne, the next is moſt ſwiftly to be clene extinct. ¶Who will not allow the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaunce of the Thraciens, the which cuſtomably vſe to receiue theim that bee borne in to this worlde, with lamentacion and mournyng: and againe whan they depart hence, they be very glad and demeane great ioye? And he that by hym ſelfe conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth inwardly thoſe thynges, that Hegeſias was wont to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to his hearers, he woulde rather deſyre his owne death than abhorre it: and wolde far more indifferently take inworth the death of his freendes. But now your fatherly ſorow com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth forth and ſaieth: He died ere his daie, he died in his child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hode,
<pb facs="tcp:9631:67"/>
he died ſo paſſyng a good childe, ye and ſo towardly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed vnto vertue, that he was worthy to haue lyued many ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res: your fatherly ſorowe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaineth, that the courſe of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is ſubuerted, ſeing that you his father an olde man, ſhould ouer lyue your ſonne a younge man. But I praie you for the loue of god tell me, what ye call before his daie: as though eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry daie of a mans life could not be his laſte daie? One before he come into this worlde, and whan vnneth it hath any ſhape of a creature reaſonable, is ſtrangled and dieth, euen vnder the handes of nature, workyng and formyng of it. An other dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the byrth. An other criyng
<pb facs="tcp:9631:68"/>
in the cradell is ſnatched awaie by death. An other in the flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng youth dieth, whan ſcarſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as yet it hath any taſt of the lyfe: Of ſo many thouſandes of people, to how few is it ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen (as Horace nameth it) to ſteppe vpon the gryce of olde age? Without doubt god hath vnder ſuche a law conſtituted the ſoule in the garriſon of this littell body, that what ſo euer moment he wyll commaunde it to depart thence, it muſt by and by nedes goe. Nor there is none that can of ryght thynke hym ſelfe to be called foorth before his daie, conſideryng that there is no man that hath a daie cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to hym appoyncted: but that onely is his lawfull daie,
<pb facs="tcp:9631:68"/>
whiche ſo euer he our ſoueraine capitaine wolde ſhoulde be his laſt daie. If we will worke wiſely, we ſhould ſo abide eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day, as it were our very laſt. I praie you, what maketh it matter, ſeyng the life is ſo ſhort and fugitiue, whether we die be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, or tary ſomwhat longer. For it ſkilleth no more than it dooeth, whan many be brought to execucion, whiche of theim ſhoulde bee fyrſt heeded or han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged: It is all one, whiche is the firſte, the third, or the eyght.</p>
            <p>And what other thing els is the lyfe it ſelfe, but a certaine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall courſe vnto death? Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing that their chaunce is more commodiouſe, the whiche from ſo laborious an exercyſe of the
<pb facs="tcp:9631:69"/>
lyfe are diſpatched betymes, But as it is a touch of a brain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les felow to depart awaie from the armie and breake the arraie, without the Capitaynes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement: So it is a fooliſhe poincte and great ingratitude, whan leaue is quickly geuen of the capitain, not gladly to take it: And moſt ſpecially, if he that hath nowe lycence to goe, maie departe his waie home with laude and praiſe, and to him no rebuke nor ſhame. Nor it is not conuenient, that one ſhould ſit and recken howe many yeares he hath lyued. The age ſhould be eſtemed accordyng to the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deedes: And he (as Homere ſaieth) is not reputed to haue lyued, that hath poyſtered the
<pb facs="tcp:9631:69"/>
earth, and made a noumbre: but he the whiche ſadde and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brely paſſyng foorth his lyfe, leaueth behynde hym an honeſt remembrance to them that come after.</p>
            <p>¶Doe ye complayne, that god ſent you foorthewith ſuche a chylde, as ye woulde deſyre to haue had many yeres to come? What, pardie your ſonne died not ſo ſoone, he was now come to the age of twentie yeres: at the which age (after myne opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion) it is beſt for to die, for ſo muche as than lyfe is mooſte ſweete. Now was he to his countrey verie bountifull, now was he to his father verie low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and gentyll, now was he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge his felowes a verie me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb facs="tcp:9631:70"/>
compaignion, and nowe had he a good and a perfecte mynde to godward. He deceſſed igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of vices, and whan he had not taſted but littell of the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitees and miſeries of this worlde. But what he ſhould haue knowen and haue felte if he had lyued longer, it is vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine. No doubte we ſee veraie often tymes, that the latter age dooeth bothe infecte the cleane conuerſacion of yong age with more greuous vyces, and ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, and defileth the felicitee of youth with manifolde miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble grefes. From all theſe euyls and perils, death quickely with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drewe hym. Nowe maie you ſafe and ſurely reioyce and be gladde, that you haue had ſo
<pb facs="tcp:9631:70"/>
good and ſo vertuous a ſonne, ye or rather haue. But be it, as you doe ſuppoſe, that you had hym, and that now ye be depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and haue loſte hym. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of veraie right oughte you rather to tourment and vexe your ſelfe for that ye haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone hym: orels reioyce and be glad that ye had ſuche a ſonne? Take you heede that it be not a poincte of vnkindneſſe, that ye ſhould remembre the requeſt of the gefte to be reſtored againe, and nothyng to minde the geft. No doubte a chylde of a good diſpoſicion is a great geft: but yet he is ſo geuen, that ye ſhould take and haue pleaſure with hym for a tyme, and not that he ſhould be yours for euer. You
<pb facs="tcp:9631:71"/>
that be a perfect wyſe man, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider this by your ſelfe, yea let vs bothe together conſider on this wyſe.</p>
            <p>¶If a great prince ſhould lend vs a table of an excedyng great price, and of an excellent work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhippe, to paſſe our tyme with: whether ought we, whan ſo euer pleaſeth him to demand or call for it, with a glad chere, ye and moreouer gentilly than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng hym, to deliuer it agayne, orels with heuie and ſorowfull countenance ſhall we complain to hym on this wyſe? O cruell prince, of how precious a gefte haſte thou ſpoyled vs? Howe great a pleaſure haſt thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raft and taken from vs? How ſoone haſt thou taken from vs,
<pb facs="tcp:9631:71"/>
contrary to our opinion this ſo excellent a thyng? Might not he of veraie right to our ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynde complaintes anſwere on this wiſe? Haue I this reward for my gentyll and courteyſe deede? Remembre ye nothyng, ſaue onely that, that ye haue forgone the moſte fayre table? Haue ye forgot, that I of myne owne good wyll and freely lent it you? And that ye haue nowe ſo long while, of my gentilneſſe and ſufferaunce fedde your eies and delyted your mynde. It was of my liberalitee and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome that I lente it you: and now whan I require it againe, I doe but right: pardie ye haue had by me ſome aduauntage, ye loſt nothyng, ſaue that through
<pb facs="tcp:9631:72"/>
your folie, ye feigned that thyng to be your owne, that was but lent you. And ſo ye eſteme it to be loſte, that is reſtored to the owner againe. But the more precious and delectable that the thyng was that I lent and leat you haue at your pleaſure, the more a great deale ye oughte to haue thanked me. Nor ye ought not to thincke it to bee to ſoone required again, the whiche with out any iniurie or wrong might haue been kept from you.</p>
            <p>¶If this reaſon can not bee proued falſe by no meane of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentacion: then thinke how much more iuſtly Nature, with ſuche maner woordes, might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue bothe our lamentacion and ſorowfull complainynges.
<pb facs="tcp:9631:72"/>
And vndoubted by theſe maner of reaſons our ſorow ought to bee ſwaged, yea if it were ſo, that a man were vtterly extinct by death, and there remained no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng of vs after the buriall.</p>
            <p>¶Now if we at the leaſt geue credence to it, whereof Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes in Plato, doubted nothyng at all, that is to witte: the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raie manne to be the ſoule, and this bodie to be nothyng els but the pype or littell howſe of the ſoule: Or els to ſaie trouth, it maie be called the burial or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the ſowle: and whan it eſcapeth out therof, than at the laſt it commeth to libertie to liue muche more welthily than it did before. Wherfore than ſhould we ſorowfully blame death, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng
<pb facs="tcp:9631:73"/>
that he that dieth, dooeth not peryſhe, but than he ſemeth rather to bee borne. And we oughte to reioyce in the ſoule (whiche we can not with our eies decerne) as much and none otherwyſe, than we be wont to reioice and take pleaſure in our frendes that bene abſent. And I doubt whether is more dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctable and reioyſyng to vs, whan they bene preſent, or els whan they bene abſent: for ſo muche as the corporall liuyng together is wonte to minyſter to vs matter of diſpleaſure, and the muche beyng in company to gether dooeth ſomewhat abate the ioyfulneſſe of frendſhip. If ye deſyre an exaumple of this thyng, be not the apoſtles a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient
<pb facs="tcp:9631:73"/>
argument, the whiche than began to take veraie frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion in Chriſte, and truely to loue him, after the corporal pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence was taken from theim? On the ſame wyſe is the frend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe of them that be good, the whiche ſtedfaſtely perſeuere in couplyng and knittyng toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the mindes, and not of the bodies. And there is no vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, no ſpace of tyme, nor no diſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of places, that can ſeuer or deuide the couplyng of myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. So that me thinke it a very childiſhe poinct, to thinke that a freende were cleane loſte and gone, ſo ſoone as he were out of ſight. You maie (as ofte as ye will) haue your ſon preſent, bothe in your thoughte and in
<pb facs="tcp:9631:74"/>
your woordes: And he (on the other ſide) remembreth you, and perceiueth the tender affections of your mynde, ye and other whyle in your ſlepe both your ſoules embrace eche other, and talke together of ſome ſecrete thynges. What thyng letteth, that ye may not euen very now imagine to liue with him, with whom ſone after ye ar in poinct to lyue? I praie you, how briefe and ſhort is all the whole tyme that we lyue here?</p>
            <p>¶Hitherto haue I vſed the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies, the whiche I might wel vſe, if I had to doe with a pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyme. Now leat vs briefely conſyder, what godlyneſſe and chriſten faieth ought to require of vs.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:9631:74"/>¶Firſt and formoſte, if it were ſo, that death were a thyng moſt miſerable: yet it behoueth vs to take it in good woorth, ſeeyng that there is none other remedie. And more ouer, if death ſhould clene extinguiſhe man, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng after ſhoulde remayne: yet we ſhould therewith be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, for as muche as it maketh an end of many calamitees and griefes, whiche we ſuffre in this lyfe. But ſeeyng that death de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuereth the ſoule (beyng of ethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall beginnyng) out of the don<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon of the ponderous and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy bodie: in a maner we ought to reioyce and be glad of theim that bee departed hence out of this wretched world: and that they be retourned home againe
<pb facs="tcp:9631:75"/>
to that welthie libertee, from whence they came. Now than conſideryng that death (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any doubt) conueieth the good deuoute ſoules out of the ſtormes of this troublous lyfe vnto the port or hauen of life per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>durable, and that not ſo muche as a heare of a mans head ſhall peryſſhe (for the bodies alſo at length ſhall be called to enioye the ſame lyfe euerlaſtyng.) I praie you, whether ought we to mourne and weepe, or els to be glad and reioyce in hym, whom death in due tyme taketh out of this moſt troublous ſea of the lyfe, and carieth hym into that quiete and ſure reſtyng place of euerlaſtyng lyfe? Goe to now a lyttell while, and laie together
<pb facs="tcp:9631:75"/>
the foule enormitees, the payn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full labours, and the perils and daungers of this lyfe, if it maie be called a lyfe. And on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſyde, recken and caſt what commoditees and pleaſures, (of that other life) are alreadie pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the godly creatures that bee plucked hence awaie: And than ye ſhall ſoone per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, that no man can do more vnrighteouſly than he, the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che lamentablie bewaileth that high goodneſſe, vnto the which onely we be both borne and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned, euen as though it were a right great and greuoꝰ harm. Ye crie out, becauſe ye bee left comfortleſſe alone without chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, whan ye haue begotte a ſonne to inhabite heauen: the
<pb facs="tcp:9631:76"/>
holy remembraunce of whom, as it were of a dyuine thyng, ye may reuerence, the whiche a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue in heauen beyng carefull for you, maie greatly further the proſperous ſucceſſe of your buſyneſſe here. For he is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ignorant of mortall folkes buſines, nor hath not forgone with the body the lowly reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and tender loue, which he was wont to beare to you his father. No doubte he lyueth, beleue me he liueth, and perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture is preſent with vs, and heareth, and perceiueth this our communicacion, and laugheth and damneth this our lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. And if the groſſenes of our bodies letted not, perchance we ſhoulde heare him blamyng
<pb facs="tcp:9631:76"/>
vs for our wepyng with thoſe maner of wordes. What doe ye? wyll ye abridge your daies, and finiſhe your olde age with this vnprofitable, ye I maye well ſaie pinyſhe lamentacion? Wherefore dooe you with ſo vniuſt complaintes accuſe and blame deſtenie, Fortune and death? Haue you enuie at me becauſe I am delyuered from the euylles of that lyfe, and am brought to this felicitee that I am in? But bee it, that your fatherly goodneſſe and pure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitee dooeth not enuy me. Yet what other thyng meaneth this ſorowfull complainyng?</p>
            <p>Thinke you this woorthy to be lamented, that I am deduct and brought from thraldome to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertee,
<pb facs="tcp:9631:77"/>
from peyne and care to pleaſure and felicitee, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vnto light, from perill and daunger vnto ſure ſafetee, from death vnto lyfe, from ſickeneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and diſeaſes vnto immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitee, from ſo many euilles to ſo high goodneſſe, from thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges caduke and tranſitorie to the euerlaſtyng, from thynges earthly to celeſtiall, and finally from the corrupt and vncleane company of all people to the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of aungels? Tell me, I praie you, for the great loue and kyndneſſe that ye beare me, If it laie in your power to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue me againe, would ye releue me? Than what offence haue I doen, to deſerue ſo great ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of you? If ye would not
<pb facs="tcp:9631:77"/>
relieue me again, than for what purpoſe ſeruen all theſe lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacions, the whiche, as I haue ſaied, are not onely vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but alſo vngodly? But ne were it ſo, that immortalitee had a while agone cleane depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued me of all ſorow, I woulde lykewyſe with weapyng teares bewayle your ſorowfull mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, and ſore haue rewed v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon thilke groſſe &amp; darke clou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe of your mynde. But ye ſay, that you on your part wepe and make lamentacion. For ſoth therin ye dooe not lyke lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers: but lyke vnto theim that haue a reſpect to theim ſelfe warde, and that wyll, to others diſcommoditee, ſee to their own buſines. Now goe to, tell me,
<pb facs="tcp:9631:78"/>
what loſſe is it, that ye ſuſteyne by my death? Is it, becauſe ye can not haue me in your ſight? Pardie ye maie neuer the leſſe, at your owne pleaſure remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre me the meane time, ye and ſo much the more welthily, in how muche I am in ſure ſafetee. For looke that ye eſteeme me nowe delyuered from all the euylles, what ſo euer they bee that maie bechaunce a mortall man in his lyfe: yf whiche your longe and robuſtous life, for a great part, hath experience. And though that I bee not with you, with lowely obeyſaunce to dooe you ſeruice, yet maie I be a ſure and an effectuall aduocate for you before the high maieſtee of god. And finally, how ſmall a thyng
<pb facs="tcp:9631:78"/>
is it, that deuideth our conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacion and familiaritee? Now loke that you ſo endeuour your ſelf, that whan ye haue wel and vertuouſly paſſed the courſe of your life, that ye may tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the houre of death be founde wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be conueied hither.</p>
            <p>If that your ſonne, I ſay, ſhuld ſaie theſe wordes to vs: myght we not well be aſhamed thus to lament and mourne as we doe? ¶With theſe maner of reſons I am wont to eaſe the griefe of myne owne mind: of the whiche I wold that you ſhuld be parte taker, not all only that ye haue any great neede of thoſe reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies: but I demed it agreable, that ye ſhuld be partaker of my conſolacion, of whoſe ſorow, I
<pb facs="tcp:9631:79"/>
was partener. But briefely to conclude, all that hath been at length reaſoned: by this maner mean, ye ſhal aſſwage the ſmar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng ſorowe of your mynde.</p>
            <p>¶My ſonne is dead, ye begot a mortall creature. I haue loſte a great iewell: ye haue yelded it again to hym that frely gaue it you. It is a right greuoꝰ thyng to be thus deſtitude: It ſhold be the lighter born, that maie be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed by ſome meane. He hath left me his father alone comfort leſſe. What doeth it auayle to weepe and wayle for that that can not bee remedied? Or why mourne you for that, the whiche chaunceth to ſo many thouſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des as well as to you? Alas I can not chooſe but wepe for the
<pb facs="tcp:9631:79"/>
death of my ſon: ye but he that dieth well, doeth in no wyſe pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſhe. But he died to ſoone: He that dieth well, dyeth not to ſoone. He died long before his daie was come: there is no man that hath a daie certein appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted vnto him. He deceſſed in his flouryng youth: It is than beſt to die whan to lyue it is moſte ſwete. He died a very yonge man: ſo is he withdrawen from the mo euyls &amp; troubles of this life. I haue loſt the beſt childe that any man coulde haue: Be glad that ye had ſuche one. He departed out of this worlde an innocent: No death ſhould be more deſired and leſſe bewailed. Ye but it is not lefull for me the meane whyle to haue fruicion
<gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
